<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to George Keith's libel. Against a catechism published by Francis Makemie. : To which is added, by way of postscript. A brief narrative of a late difference among the Quakers, begun at Philadelphia.</title>
            <author>Makemie, Francis, 1658-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W24940</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171419</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171419)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2573:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to George Keith's libel. Against a catechism published by Francis Makemie. : To which is added, by way of postscript. A brief narrative of a late difference among the Quakers, begun at Philadelphia.</title>
                  <author>Makemie, Francis, 1658-1708.</author>
                  <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 103, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, by Benjamin Harris, at the sign of the Bible, over-against the Blew-Anchor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIIII. [i.e. 1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An epistle to the reader" dated and signed: At Rehoboth in Pocamok Maryland. This 26 July, 1692. Francis Makemie.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Increase Mather March 31st, 1694"--T.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>"Christian reader" (p. [3-5], 1st grouping) signed: Increase Mather, James Allen, Samuel Baily, Cotton Mather.</note>
                  <note>"A true copy of George Keith's paper ...": p. 5-19.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, stained, and cropped with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:2"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO George Keith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Libel. Againſt A CATECHISM Publiſhed, by <hi>Francis Make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> To which is Added, by way of
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</hi> A Brief
Narrative of a Late Difference among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun at
<hi>Philadelphia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON,</hi> Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed, by <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the BIBLE, over-ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. MDCXCIIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:3"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Increaſe Mather</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>March
31ſt. 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ch is, not only the <hi>Impiety, Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and
<hi>Contradiction</hi> to clear Scripture Light, which the Doctrine of the
<hi>Quakers</hi> is ſtuffed withal; but the <hi>Unreaſonableneſs,
Nonſenſe,</hi> and <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contradiction,</hi> which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arries with it; that it may well
ſeem a wonder to men of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding, that it hath not long ſince been
Exploded: and that the Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it have not been a ſhame and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule to
themſelves, and one to another<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
and that it had not died alone, if no attempts had been made against it by ſo
many worthy Champions of the Truth: and indeed there can be no other account
given of it, but that God, in his awful and righteous Judgment, hath left men
to <hi>Believe a Lie, becauſe they received
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the Truth in the Love of
it:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:6"/>ſo, <hi>a Deceived Heart hath turned them aſide,
that they cannot ſay, is there not a Lie in our Right hand?</hi> and were it
not that there are ſo many, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring of ſuch ignorance, as to think that
holding our peace, were a yielding up the cauſe, it were pity, at this time
of day, to take ſo much notice of their Scriblings, as to waste Paper in
replying upon them. But ſince there is a kind of a neceſſity for it,
leſt the <hi>ſacred Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> ſhould ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſome, not ſufficiently defended without it, it may not be thought
unadviſable to comply with the ſecond part of the Wiſemans
<hi>Antitheſis,</hi> Prov. 26.5. and, though no Truth is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> foregone, yet when the Foundations
ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtricken at, and thoſe
Articles on which our hopes for Eternal Life are built, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermined, it is time to arm in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of
them.</p>
            <p>The following Diſcourſes then will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found both ſeaſonable and profitable,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which the venome and
ſophistry of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rand
<hi>Apoſtate,</hi> and one of the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> caried Supporters
of that totteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:6"/>Fabrick of <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> are detected; and the perverſe
ſpirit which God hath ſown among them, in ſuffering them to lay open each
others follies, is diſcovered by the Reverend and Judicious Author. We do
therefore Commend him, and theſe Labours of his to the Bleſſing of God,
who alone can <hi>recover the fallen, ſettle the wavering, and confirm ſuch
as ſtand,</hi> and make the faithful Endeavours <hi>of</hi> this his Servant
<hi>become</hi> inſtrumental <hi>to</hi> theſe Deſired Ends.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed> 
                  <list>
                     <item>Increaſe Mather.</item>
                     <item>Iames Allen</item>
                     <item>Samuel Willard</item>
                     <item>Iohn Baily</item>
                     <item>Cotton Mather</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:7"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot but admire the Instability of many who are ſo eaſily,
and ſoon drawn to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and Eſpouſe that perſwaſion and way of
thoſe called Quakers, and that becauſe of an outward and ſeeming
<hi>Sanctity,</hi> that is to be found, and to be diſcerned among many of
them conſiſting only in Negatives, making up a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical
Righteouſneſs, made of thoſe things that are not peculiar to
<hi>Quakers</hi> only, of not <hi>Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Drinking,</hi> and
<hi>Ranting:</hi> but if they would but cautiouſly Look, before they Leap,
they would find the principles of many of the Reformed <hi>Churches</hi> as
much againſt all thoſe, and many more evils, as theirs can be, and
thouſands of Profeſſors exceed them in a ſhining Holineſs, and
Chriſtian Univerſal Piety; and though others walk diſorderly, and not
anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, is not to be imputed to our
Profeſſion, Principles or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worſhipping God; otherwiſe all
Religion would ſoon be rejected, and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> it ſelf would be
ſoon deſerted. The moſt of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is compoſed of Negatives;
for many of<pb facs="tcp:171419:8"/>them are as void of the poſitive part of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as
worſhipping God in the publick, private and ſecret Duties of Religion, as
many moral Heathens, who if they had but Learned their uſual tone, and grown
ſullen and unmannerly, might paſs for <hi>Quakers</hi> all over the world.
If we take a view of their principles in believing every one of them
ſeverally by themſelves, and the Books of particular Writers, they are not
on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to truth, contrary to Gods Word, and the publick received
Doctrine of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt for many Centurys paſt; but alſo
dangerous and damnable. They cannot be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as a Church, having not
unanimouſly-and fairly, or faithfully publiſhed all their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and
principles, which is the cauſe many Eſpouſe they know not what; they have
not in any of their Writings declared their Church Order, Conſtitution,
Government nor Diſcipline. They have no orderly way of Admiſſion for
Teaching Officers, but as many men, &amp; women, as ſay, the Spirit of the
Lord is upon them, muſt be received, though they can give no convincing
proof, but to thoſe already Deluded to their way from which they want the
pure and powerful Preaching of the Goſpel, and all Adminiſtration of
Sacraments, which they ſlightly ridicule, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than own; they hold or
maintain a common Chriſt in all, even in the Reprobate, in whom the Spirit of
God ſays, Chriſt is not; &amp; a ſufficient<pb facs="tcp:171419:8"/>ſaving Light,
and grace in all, even the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Darkneſs, denying Original and
Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Guilt in any Infants, even in their natural State; Railing againſt
Singing of Pſalms, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Reſurrection of the ſame Body; many of
them ſcoff at the Imputed Righteouſneſs of Christ for our
Juſtification, and Salvation, maintaining an abſolute perfection for many
years in this Life, by a Popiſh Poſſbility of keeping all Gods Commands,
of which neither they, nor Papiſt could ever in any age produce one known
Instance.</p>
            <p>Reader, I offer here ſome Sheets to thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial peruſal,
which was occaſioned by a Paper writ by <hi>George Keith,</hi> and delivered
by his own hands into the hands of Mr. <hi>George Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> at
<hi>Rehoboth</hi> in <hi>Pocamok,</hi> from whence as many as read, may ſoon
conclude, this debate was firſt ſet on foot by themſelves, and by
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting, it gave occaſion for Laying open both their Principles, and their
practiſes, more in theſe corners of the World, then they have yet been. In
which Anſwer, I have given Reply to all the Calumnies and Charges in that
Paper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my Catechiſm, which I am obliged to Juſtifie and Defend. And
the only Apology why I have not Enlarged in the proof of ſome points, and
particularly of our Doctrine concerning the Sabbath, though I have
ſufficiently vindicated my Charge, becauſe they are fully handled by
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<pb facs="tcp:171419:9"/>And concerning this Subject, I Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <hi>Keith</hi>
and all of them to <hi>Caudree</hi> and <hi>Palmer,</hi> Mr. <hi>John
Brown,</hi> ſometime of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Matthew Crawford;</hi>
and whoever anſwers them, ſhall anſwer me; If any ſhould Cenſure me
for my tediouſneſs in anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>I</hi> had finiſhed it a year
ago, but by reaſon of my tedious Affliction, not Tranſcribed until now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I had a viſit from</hi> Keith <hi>at my houſe in</hi>
Virginia, <hi>which though promiſed and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by his Harbinger to be
on</hi> Fryday, <hi>was not performed until</hi> Saturday, <hi>in the
Afternoon, &amp; by the uncertainty of their coming, was prevented of having
any of my Friends preſent, though ſome few drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in occaſionally, at
which time we had ſeveral Charges and Queſtions, concerning ſeveral
things, which were too tedious to Rehearſe here: but I wiſh they had been
Recorded then, to prevent many miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, that were ſpread abroad by that Party. And
though there was no real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; &amp; he oft told me, he came not to
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with me, yet ſoon after they boaſted of a Victory; which if they
find after a diligent peruſal, &amp; impartial conſideration of theſe
Sheets, let them improve and poſt it if they will.</hi> Yet after ſome
Diſcourſe, be impudently charged me as a Falſe Teacher, and<pb facs="tcp:171419:9"/>challenged me to a <hi>Publick</hi> Diſpute before the Multitude,
which <hi>I</hi> ſcorned with a ſharp retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that for theſe
reaſons: 1. Their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were unknown, becauſe never
<hi>unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> agreed upon, nor <hi>fairly</hi> Publiſhed to the
World, therefore not to be Diſputed within words. 2. We <hi>ſhould</hi>
Diſpute before an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and illeterate <hi>Multitude,</hi> who
<hi>ſhould</hi> be moſt incompetent Judges. 3. Becauſe he would run into
Learning, and <hi>I</hi> muſt follow, and ſo what <hi>ſhould</hi> be
<hi>Delivered,</hi> ſhould not tend to their Edification, but fall to the
ground, and be Loſt. But afterwards <hi>I</hi> gave him a <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</hi>
to oppoſe my Catechiſm, or <hi>Principles</hi> in Writing, and he
<hi>ſhould</hi> have an Anſwer to every <hi>Particular;</hi> though
<hi>Keith</hi> gave not the <hi>leaſt</hi> intimation of this Paper left
behind him, though he dropt an Expreſſion, which <hi>I</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
not then, that he <hi>would</hi> Write no more then he had done; this
<hi>I</hi> took for <hi>Declining</hi> my Challenge: Now <hi>I</hi> Leave it to
<hi>all</hi> to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine whoſe <hi>Challenges</hi> or Overture was
faireſt, for 1. What either of us <hi>ſhould Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhould</hi> be on
Record, and we could not fly from it. 2 <hi>If</hi> the Hearing a verbal
Debate, in angry words, <hi>ſhould</hi> Edifie, much more a written Debate,
<hi>frequently</hi> read over. 3. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y might be Judges of a written Debate, who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad no opportunity of hearing it
<hi>Diſputed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ublickly.</hi> And
as I have prefixed his Paper<pb facs="tcp:171419:10"/>verbatim, <hi>ſo</hi> I <hi>expect
the ſame priviledge for mine,</hi> if <hi>any Anſwer is Publiſhed.</hi> I
<hi>have greater and better work then Controverſie to Follow; but in the
Strength</hi> of <hi>the Lord, ſhall not only Defend my Principles ſtill by
Writing, but</hi> if <hi>called thereunto, ſhall rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily Seal them with my Blood. And ſo I Leave thee
Reader to the Counſel, and Direction</hi> of <hi>God, whoſe Unworthy
Servant I am in the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At <hi>Rehoboth in Pocamok</hi> Maryland. This 
<date>26 July, 1692.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Francis
Makemie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I alſo offer thee, theſe Following Queſtions which I expect
and deſire Reſolution and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, from</hi> ſuch as are
concerned, and that Plainly, Poſitively, Sincerely and Faithfully, according
to the Judgment <hi>of</hi> all <hi>of</hi> that Party, without Obſcurity,
Equivocation, or Subtile and Unfair Reſervation, and ſo <hi>I</hi> bid
the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Farewel, and Remains as
above</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_questions">
            <list>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171419:10"/>
               <head>Several mixed Quaeries, to be reſolved by <hi>Quakers</hi>
in this juncture, for the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of themſelves and ſatisfaction
of all. 
<date>July 26th. 1692.</date>
               </head>
               <item>(<hi>Queſtion</hi> I.) WHat is the Reaſon
<hi>Quakers</hi> are ſo far Metamorphoſed, or Changed, both in Judgment,
and Practice at this Day, from what they once were, at their firſt riſe in
<hi>Europe?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. What is the Reaſon <hi>Quakers</hi> that look upon
themſelves, as the only pure Church in the World, has never yet adventured to
Publiſh a form of ſound words according to the Apoſtles language,
containing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith, and principles, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly
agreed upon among themſelves, as all other churches in the world have
done.</item>
               <item>III Seeing they own themſelves divinely inſpired from an
immediate call, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick miſſion, why they have not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to
publiſh interpretations of Scripture ſeeing they condemn &amp; ſo far
diſapprove all other Commentaries, as far from the mind of God, and full of
groſs Errors, and miſtakes.</item>
               <item>IV Wherefore did they write, and Bark ſo much againſt all
witneſſing to truth,<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171419:11"/>conviction of falſhood, in
Judicatures by an oath, as ſinful, and unlawful under the Goſpel, and now
in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and <hi>Mary-Land,</hi> ſeem only to quarrel, the
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and way of Swearing on the Book ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Form, and are willing to Swear now in Judicatures, with lifted up hands, which
many look upon to be more ſolemn than the former?</item>
               <item>V. Whether it be the ſame individual nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Body for
ſubſtance which falleth that ſhall riſe again at the Reſurrection,
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Changes, in Reſpect of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity?</item>
               <item>VI. If there be a ſufficient and ſaving light in all men
to inſtruct, direct, and to teach them; what neceſſity is there for
mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying ſo many Teachers, both of Men and Women, among
<hi>Quakers?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VII. Why <hi>Quakers</hi> are ſo hot, and Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for K.
<hi>James,</hi> a Popiſh and Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prince, and was never ſo for any
other Proteſtant King, tho' King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY</hi> has
been kinder than any other, by giving a Liberty eſtabliſhed by Law?</item>
               <item>VIII. Whether the ſame individual Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that was
cloathed with Heſh, ſuffered, and died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is the
ſame that roſe again, and is aſcended to Glory, and the<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171419:11"/>ſame they hold ſubſtantially in all men and women?</item>
               <item>IX How Chriſt, the Spirit of God, ſaving Grace, and Light
can be in thoſe, who have not the leaſt knowledg of him as Mediator and
Interceſſour between God and ſinners.</item>
               <item>X Whether the omiſſion of duty, as prayer or any other
duty for a certain time, a week, a month, or a year, is excuſable in
<hi>Quakers,</hi> before an all-ſeeing and Juſt God from this pretence,
that they had no impulſe or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit thereunto.</item>
               <item>XI Why they uſe not means for edifying &amp; reforming
thoſe of their families, by calling <hi>them</hi> together, reading Scripture
daily to <hi>them</hi> &amp; praying with &amp; for them, as other
<hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians</hi> in all Churches, and Ages have done, and is approved in
the Word of God.</item>
               <item>XII Wherefore <hi>Quakers</hi> have not adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<hi>to</hi> publiſh their doctirnes publick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>taught,</hi> which they ſay is immediate from the ſpirit
of God, as moſt other Churches have done frequently.</item>
               <item>XIII Seeing they decry the civil ſalutations of the
Kingdom, &amp; people, among <hi>whom they</hi> live, what warrant can they
produce for their ſingular, ugly, &amp; bad natured way of ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
their Males &amp; Females taking one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother by the hands or wriſts,
continuing a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſiderable
ſpace, wringing them hard, &amp; <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171419:12"/>looking ſtedfaſtly in
each others faces, without one word ſpeaking.</item>
               <item>XIV Whether it is Chriſt compleatly as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, you
believe in, and is in all men.</item>
               <item>XV Whether two men differing in a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental truth,
abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation can be guided by the ſame
infallible Spirit.</item>
               <item>XVI. Whether Quakers do direct their Prayers to God in
<hi>themſelves,</hi> or to God in Heaven.</item>
               <item>XVII Where God is really, perſonally, &amp;
ſubſtantially; is he not in all fulneſs of Grace and Goodneſs.</item>
               <item>XVIII What Worſhip, or Divine Service do the heathen
nations perform unto the Living, and True God.</item>
               <item>XIX Whether the inflicting of corporal puniſhments on
children, ſervants, &amp; other offenders, and hiring of men to take a
Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel by force from Privateers, be not an uſing of the carnal
Weapon.</item>
               <item>XX Whether the receiving of a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent maintainance, or
neceſſary Aliment by Quaker teachers, however ſo freely and Voluntarily
given, without appointment of humane law, and all compulſion, be a Preaching
the Goſpel freely.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="copy_of_paper">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:171419:12"/>
            <head>A True Copy of George Keith's Paper, Delivered to Mr. George
Layfield, At <hi>POCAMOK</hi> in <hi>MARY-LAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>KIND Friend <hi>George Lay-field,</hi> my Dear Love in the Lord
Jeſus Chriſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteth thee, with Earneſt Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Prayer to God
for thee, that God, who hath begun his good work in thee, may perfect it, until
the Day of Chriſt, and that the Precious Seed, that God hath Sown in thy
Heart may grow not only to be the greateſt of Herbs, but a great Tree,
bringing forth Fruit, to Gods Everlaſting Praiſe, and to thy Souls
Everlaſting Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Happineſs.</p>
            <p>As concerning the Catechiſm, Publiſhed by <hi>F. M.</hi> I
have diligently read, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dered it, and tho' it holdeth forth diverſe true things, yet it
hath a great mixture of Error, and many falſe, and unſound hurtful things
it doth contain; which my preſent ſhortneſs of time in theſe Parts,
doth not permit me to mention in moſt particulars; and as the ſame
Catechiſm aboundeth<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171419:13"/>with many Errors; ſo it falleth
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſhort, in not mentioning in the leaſt, many neceſſary
Truths, and Doctrines, which are of great neceſſity, to be taught unto
people, as belonging to the firſt Principles of Chriſtian Religion, which
he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together omitteth; nor doth he in the leaſt declare that he receiveth
any one of theſe things, delivered by him, in his ſaid Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, from
any inward opening or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Gods Spirit in his Heart: Nor doth he
mention, any one thing of his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, of the work of God in his heart,
but as his Title Page ſheweth, his whole Work is but a Collection from
others; he mentions nothing in all his Catechiſm, that people are to be
turned or directed to God, or Chriſt, or the Spirit of God in them, he
telleth not People, that it is God or Chriſt, or the Spirit of God convinceth
them, and reproveth them for ſins of all ſorts, as Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Pride, Envy,
Coveteouſneſs, Unbelief he doth not inſtruct People, how they are to find
God and Chriſt in their Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
and how they are to wait in ſilence
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mind, and thoughts, to hear
God, and Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak inwardly
unto them in their Heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the
ſilence of all Fleſh; and how the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are to have God and Chriſt, and the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit to <hi>dwell</hi> and <hi>walk</hi> in them,
and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>teach</hi> them over and
beyond all outwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171419:13"/>
               <hi>teaching;</hi> he mentions very little of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit at
all, and what he mentions of it is, very <hi>Obſcurely,</hi> ſo that
without breach of <hi>Charity,</hi> I can freely ſay, he is a great Stranger
to the <hi>inward Dealings and Workings of Gods Holy Spirit in the Hearts of
his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> and whereas he mentions, his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion over the Tender
Souls, in an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merican Deſart,</hi> ready to periſh for want of a
<hi>Viſion,</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader;</hi> his
<hi>Catechiſm</hi> can nothing help them in that reſpect; for not one word
in all his <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> directeth People were to find the true
<hi>Viſion</hi> of God in any meaſure; but on the contrary, according to
<hi>his,</hi> and <hi>his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therens</hi> Falſe Faith, all true Divine
<hi>Viſion,</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> and all Divine
<hi>Inſpiration,</hi> is ceaſed ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Days, both
among <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and God hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted His
Counſel wholly to Writing, the former ways of Gods revealing himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ceaſed; and they ſay further; there is no inward voice, or word of God in
people, but the <hi>Scripture</hi> is the only Word, and only Rule, all which
is moſt falſe, and hurtful <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and doth more hurt where it
is received, then all his <hi>Catechiſm</hi> can do good. And all the People
in <hi>Virginia</hi> both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> whom he
ſeemeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon for their Ignorance, have the Holy Scriptures
without, and the Holy<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171419:14"/>teachings, and illuminations of God and
Chriſt within, to teach them what is needful to their Salvation, if they will
hearken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, far better then this <hi>Catehiſm</hi> of <hi>F M.</hi>
which is defective, and wanting of many Principal and neceſſary doctrines,
belonging to the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the firſt Page of his</hi> Catechiſm, <hi>He ſaith,
God made the World out of Nothing;</hi> but this is no Scripture Language and
indeed in very many of his Anſwers, he holdeth not to Scripture Language, but
uſeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented words of Mans Wiſdom, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but contrary unto
the Holy Scriptures. May it not ſuffice to ſay, <hi>God Created a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> as
the Scriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, without adding to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Third.</hi> He mentions no other <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> but
the <hi>Scriptures</hi> given to men, to ſerve and Glorify God; And thus
according to him; all theſe great Nations who have not the
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> are wholly left without all Teaching of God to Serve and
Glorify him, in the leaſt meaſure, but this is expreſly contrary to
<hi>Scripture,</hi> which ſay concerning the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who had not
the Law outwardly delivered in Scripture, that they did ſhow the work of the
Law in their hearts, and what was to be known of God, was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in them;
for God had ſhown it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171419:14"/>them, and when they knew God,
they Glorified him not as God and Chriſt the Light of the World, hath
enlightned every man that cometh into the World; and teacheth every man in
ſome meaſure to ſerve God, which is to obey him, otherwiſe they could
not have ſin; if there were nothing in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to require
obedience or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of them unto God.</p>
            <p>It had been much better in this <hi>Authour</hi> to have
inſtructed People, that they had ſome other helps, and means of knowledge
with the Scriptures, and theſe ſome outward, and ſome inward, although it
is to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the Scriptures are the beſt of all <hi>Books</hi>
outward, yet there is the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Gods Creation,</hi> and the
<hi>Book</hi> of His <hi>Providence over all his Creatures;</hi> that are no
ſmall helps and means, in their place being duely uſed and together with
God, Chriſt, and the Spirit, are inwardly preſent to teach all People, in
ſome things to ſerve God, and as every one is faithful in the little, more
is given to them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that the Writer of this <hi>Catechiſm</hi> ſhould
have joined the ſpirit of God &amp; Chriſt with the Scriptures, as the
<hi>Opener,</hi> &amp; <hi>Interpreter</hi> of them, informing people that the
Scriptures are the <hi>Organ</hi> &amp; <hi>Instrument</hi> of Gods Spirit;
&amp; that Gods Good, and Holy Spirit, is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Author and cauſe of
all true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171419:15"/>of God, as he doth inwardly inſpire,
and enlighten every one; and that there is no true ſaving knowledge of God,
and Chriſt, without the Spirits Inſpiration, and Teaching; and that how
much ſoever peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple read or hear the Scriptures, if they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or turn
away their minds from Gods inward teachings, by his Word, Spirit, and Light
within their hearts, they remain Blind, and Dark; and Ignorant of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Third.</hi> That he ſaith there are <hi>Three Perſons
in the God-head;</hi> this is not Scripture Language, to ſay Three Perſons,
<hi>The Myſtery of the Three,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Father</hi> the
<hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> who are One GOD, is Great, and
Glorious, and ought to be Reverently conceived &amp; expreſſed, in
Scripture words, which the Holy-Ghoſt hath Taught; but not in words of Mans
Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Ninth &amp; Tenth.</hi> In mentioning the Offices of
Chriſt, being Three, <hi>Viz. Prophet Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>King;</hi> he
ſhould have mentioned how that not only without us, he did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form theſe
Offices, and now is both <hi>Prieſt and King in Heaven,</hi> whither he is
aſcended but that alſo within us. <hi>Viz.</hi> All true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in him,
he is both <hi>Prophet,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> alſo,
who offereth up their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto God, and by whom they have acceſs unto
God, beſide that Chriſt is not<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171419:15"/>only, <hi>King,
Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> over his Church; but <hi>Biſhop,
Shepherd, Phyſitian, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and <hi>Husband,</hi> &amp;c. as the
Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth:</p>
            <p>And that he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt revealeth the Will of God to us,
by His Word and Spirit; in Page</hi> 10. He delivereth this matter very barely,
and obſcurely; for he does not tell people where they may find the Spirit of
God; he doth not inſtruct them, <hi>That the Spirit of God is in them to
teach them, and open the Scriptures unto them:</hi> And tho' he delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
diverſe things in his <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the New Covenant, yet
he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecteth a Principal matter belonging to the ſame; <hi>Viz. That God
hath Promiſed, in his New Covenant, to teach His People Himſelf, and to
dwell in them, and walk in them, and that they ſhall be his Temple.</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 10 11. <hi>Although he mention the death and
Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt for ſinners,</hi> yet he doth not well, that
he doth not hold forth that <hi>Chriſt died for all, and taſted Death for
eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man,</hi> as the Scripture expreſly declareth: which is a moſt
great, and weighty teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods univerſal Love for
<hi>ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Eleventh.</hi> Tho' he ſay, <hi>The Holy Spirit worketh
faith in us,</hi> and <hi>Uniteth us to Christ,</hi> yet he doth this very
barely, and obſcurely, yea in contradiction to <hi>his</hi> and 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171419:16"/>
               <hi>his Brethrens Doctrine;</hi> who ſay, all inward
Divine Revelation, and Inſpiration is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſince the
<hi>Apoſtles</hi> Days, &amp; if ſo then the Holy Spirit hath ceaſed to
work or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate on mens hearts, for his operation is not in the dark, or in a
blind and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible manner, but in Light, and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,
ſenſibly, and clearly, revealing his power in them, &amp; opening the eyes
of their underſtanding; and thence it is that the Spirit of God, is called in
Scripture, the Spirit of Wiſdom, and Revelation, and that Spirit worketh in
true Beleivers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Eleventh.</hi> That he calleth <hi>Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> a
<hi>New and Spiritual Birth, by the Spirit of God,</hi> is true, but this
Contradicteth <hi>His,</hi> and <hi>His Brethrens</hi> Doctrine, who ſay,
they have no infallible Spirit, and all Divine Revelation is ceaſed, and that
there is no immediate communion with God or his Spirit which is <hi>Falſe
Doctrine,</hi> and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Scripture, and the <hi>Saints</hi> Experience,
who know that as they are Born of Gods Spirit, ſo they are ſenſibly
<hi>Fed,</hi> and <hi>Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed</hi> by the Spirit of God, and <hi>Suck the
Breaſts of their Heavenly Mother, Jeruſalem from above;</hi> and feel
themſelves embraced by the ſame, as ſenſibly as the <hi>Child</hi>
feeleth the <hi>Mothers Embraces,</hi> and ſee and behold <hi>Her
Beauty,</hi> hear <hi>her voice,</hi> and <hi>Language,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:171419:16"/>and all this is Spiritually, and Inwardly known and witneſſed in
all True Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>Again, that he ſaith, <hi>True Believers are United to
Christ;</hi> is true, and very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but is in contradiction to
<hi>His</hi> and <hi>his Brethrens Doctrine;</hi> who ſay it is Blaſphemy
to affirm, that Chriſt is really in the Saints, for if he be not really in
them, by himſelf, they cannot be <hi>United</hi> to him, for true
<hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> requireth the near preſence of the things <hi>United</hi> one
to another, as the <hi>Body</hi> cannot be <hi>United</hi> to the
<hi>Soul,</hi> if the <hi>Soul</hi> be not really in the <hi>Body,</hi> and all
true Believers are <hi>United to Chriſt in Heaven,</hi> by their being
<hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited</hi> to the meaſure of him in themſelves, as the Members of the
<hi>Body</hi> are <hi>United</hi> to the <hi>Head,</hi> by being
<hi>United</hi> to a meaſure of the ſame Life, and Spirit in them, that is
in the <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Eleven Twelve.</hi> He defineth Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Calling, to
be, <hi>A powerful call of God, whereby he calls, and draws ſinners out of
Sin into Grace,</hi> which as it is true, ſo is in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to
<hi>him</hi> and <hi>his Brethren,</hi> who ſay, <hi>All inward calling, and
ſpeaking of God is ceaſed, and there is no other Voice, or Word of God, but
the Scriptures;</hi> and yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, all have not that
<hi>Effectual Calling,</hi> who have the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Again, he
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cradicteth, by ſaying, that <hi>God calleth, and 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171419:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>draweth ſinners out of ſin, unto Grace;</hi> and
yet in <hi>Page Twelve,</hi> ſaith, <hi>All are ſtill ſinners;</hi> And
in <hi>Page Thirty,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Godly cannot keep Gods commands
perfectly:</hi> And <hi>His Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns Doctrine is,</hi> that the <hi>Saints
ſin in every Though:, Word, and Deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Fifteen.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Juſtification, and
Adoption, are acts of God without us, and make only a Relative change, but no
real change, and are compleated at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Page Sixteen.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
Adoption, and Sanctification, once had, can never be wanted;</hi> all which are
Falſe, and hurtful Aſſertions, and contrary to Scripture; for Gods
Juſtifying Believers, is his ſpeaking peace to them in their
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and Abſolving them from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as a <hi>Judge</hi>
abſolveth or cleareth an <hi>Accuſed Perſon,</hi> and ſurely that is
within and if not within, he ſhould have told where without; if he mean in
Heaven, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can be no
aſſurance nor comfort to any, unleſs it be revealed, and done alſo
within in mens hearts: Again, that <hi>God maketh any men to be his Children,
without a Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> is
moſt abſurd, is not <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Regeneration,</hi> a <hi>real
change;</hi> and none are made the <hi>children</hi> of God, but by
<hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Regeneration:</hi> and again, to ſay that
<hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification, cannot be loſt,</hi> is
mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> abſurd, and ſerveth to
flatter people i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:171419:17"/>great ſins, yea the greateſt, as if they were ſtill
<hi>Saints;</hi> for according to this <hi>Falſe Doctrine, David</hi>
remained a <hi>Saint</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly <hi>Juſtified,</hi> when he
committed <hi>Murder,</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> and at this rate, the worſt
of men may be <hi>Saints</hi> while ſuch; but the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith,
<hi>No Murderer, nor Unrighteous Perſon, can Inherit the Kingdom of God, but
they muſt be waſhed.</hi> &amp;c. But if they ſtill remain
<hi>Saints</hi> after <hi>Murder,</hi> they may <hi>inherit Gods Kingdom,</hi>
for all the <hi>Saints</hi> are in meaſure in <hi>Gods Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Twenty-four.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Sabbath</hi> he
expreſly Contradicteth the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which expreſly enjoyned
<hi>the ſeventh Day to be kept,</hi> and not indifferently <hi>one of
ſeven</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Twenty-ſix.</hi> He moſt groſly wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and
moſt falſely accuſeth the People of God, called in ſcorn
<hi>Quakers,</hi> ſaying that the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and all <hi>Profane
Perſons</hi> are <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> but it is no new,
nor ſtrange thing that Gods <hi>People</hi> is numbred with
<hi>Tranſgreſſors</hi> of the <hi>greatest ſort,</hi> ſeeing Chriſt
<hi>our</hi> Lord and Head, was ſo uſed by men <hi>high in an outward
Profeſſion,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> called <hi>Quakers</hi> own
Chriſt to be the True Spiritual <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or <hi>Rest</hi> of all
True Believers, the ſubſtance, and thing ſignified by the <hi>Jewiſh
Sabbaths,</hi> and <hi>New Moons,</hi> and other <hi>Types</hi> and
<hi>Figures</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> yet they ſet apart the <hi>Firſt day
of the week</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171419:18"/>from Servile Labour, and ſpend it
Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in Publick and Private Religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes as their
Neighbours can witneſs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom they live; and give up no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only that Day, but many other days,
an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times to the Worſhip of God,
and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> careful to live to God all
the days o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Twenty-eight.</hi> What he delivereth in his
<hi>Catechiſm</hi> concerning <hi>Miniſters,</hi> is moſt <hi>Lame,</hi>
and <hi>Defective:</hi> He ſaith, <hi>People
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to maintain their Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſters</hi> [that is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
thing with him] but he faileth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
theſe Three great Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he doth not inform people, that none are true
<hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as are really Holy and Godly Men, and have a Living
Experience of the work and dealings of Gods Spirit in their heart that ſo
they may Preach their own Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Experiences unto people, as <hi>Davi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did, who ſaid, <hi>Come, and I
will tell you wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God hath done for
my ſoul;</hi> and as <hi>theſe</hi> did who ſaid, <hi>What we have heard,
and ſeen, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> handled of the word
of Life, we declare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he doth not inform People concerning the true Call
of the true <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi>
of God, and of Chriſt, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
called, and furniſhed by the Spirit of Chaiſt in the work of their
Miniſtry, to Preach<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171419:18"/>and Pray, but ſeeing <hi>he</hi> and
<hi>his Brethren,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters, deny this
manner of immediate calling by the Spirit of God, they run to the
<hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> by that Dirty <hi>Channel,</hi> and
<hi>Conduit,</hi> to have their Call conveyed to them; for they know that their
<hi>Presbyterian Church,</hi> nor indeed any other called a Church, hath been a
Viſible Church, ever ſince the <hi>Apostles</hi> Days, but only the Church
of <hi>Rome</hi> hath called her ſelf the Viſible Church; and they
confeſs, and ſay with us, that the True Church of God hath been that
<hi>Woman</hi> who hath fled to the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and hath not been
always viſible, but hid, and that for about Twelve Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years, and ſo
had no viſible Officers or Miniſters, to call their ſucceſſors: And
therefore they derive their Call, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by the Church, and <hi>Pope of
Rome;</hi> as <hi>James Durham.</hi> in his Commentary on the
<hi>Revelations,</hi> and many others, whoſe Call and Ordination, Dr.
<hi>Owen,</hi> ſo called, hath refuted, and theſe called
<hi>Independent</hi> Miniſters, whereof <hi>John Owen</hi> was one, have
another poor ſhift, and evaſion, ſaying they are called by the Church;
but if the Church was not viſible for ſo many ages, the Church could not
call them, the Miniſters are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church, and therefore cannot be
called by the Church originally; but all theſe poor ſhifts are in
oppoſition to the<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171419:19"/>inward Call, and work, and motion of
Gods Spirit in the hearts of the Faithful, which if they knew, they would never
run to ſuch broken <hi>Cyſterns</hi> to Draw <hi>Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That he doth not inform people, that all true Miniſters
of Chriſt, as they have freely received, ſo they freely give, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
deſiring or bargaining for any ſetled maintenance, nor exacting it by force
as <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters commonly do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page Thirty Nine &amp; Forty.</hi> He doth very barely, and
obſcurely, and very defectively and in ſome things falſly deliver his
Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine concerning <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Lords-Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> he doth not diſtinguiſh
Chriſts <hi>Baptiſm</hi> which is with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> and
<hi>Fire,</hi> from <hi>Johns Baptiſm,</hi> that is with <hi>Water;</hi> he
bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alledgeth, that Children of Believing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Viz. <hi>Infants are
to be Baptized;</hi> he giveth no account by what Authority o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Call they <hi>Baptiſe,</hi> for they
have no other Call but by the <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> and they have learned that
practice of Sprinking or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water on a Childs Forehead, and calling it
<hi>Baptiſm</hi> from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> which they call the
<hi>Where of Babylon;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
concerning the <hi>Supper of the Lord,</hi> he is alſo very defective, and
<hi>he</hi> and <hi>his Brethren</hi> uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and aſſume an Authority to themſelve to Conſecrate, and
Adminiſter the Supper<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171419:19"/>becauſe of their Ordination
originally deriv'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the
<hi>Pope;</hi> but all good Chriſtians ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ought to Eat and Drink, remembring Chriſts Death, and may,
and do receive him by Faith, together with their outward eating, with Prayer,
and Thankſgiving, and ſo fulfil Chriſts Inſtitution, without any
<hi>Prelate, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi>
making; for all true Chriſtians are a Kingdom of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> unto
God, and have the Word, and Spirit of Prayer, that only doth, and can Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy
their Eating and Drinking. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <argument>
               <p>If any Queſtion the Truth of this <hi>Copy,</hi> they may
ſatisfie themſelves by peruſing the Original, at <hi>Rehoboth</hi> in
<hi>Pocamok, Mary-Land.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171419:20"/>
            <head>A Short Anſwer, to George Keith's Lybel, Againſt a
CATECHISM Publiſhed, by <hi>F. M.</hi> And left in the Hands of, Mr. George
Layfield.</head>
            <p>I Am not a little ſurpriſed to receive from the hands of Mr
<hi>George Layfield</hi> a paper containing ſo many miſtakes, falſe,
unjuſt, and invidous charges againſt a Catechiſm Publiſhed by <hi>F
M.</hi> and the rather becauſe of his high pretences to an immideate
miſion, and vain boaſting of an extraordinary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick call,
iuſulting over all others from unuſual high and enthuſiaſtick
attainments compleat perfection, and unheard of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, which the moſt
ſerious and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ſtrangers unto and what they have any experince of
moſt modeſt in diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them and ſelfe denyed under their
greateſt enjoyments I ſhall wave two things Firſt it's being delivered
without a ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171419:20"/>whereby it is to be looked upon
as a Libel not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be Anſwered,
nor Regarded. Secondly, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing and flattering preamble, they have
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Condemned</hi> in others, and withal am glad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hear they have any Charity for
any of a different Opinion from themſelves, which coming to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Teachers will procure at any
time. Firſt, He begins with a general Charge of many <hi>Errors, falſe</hi>
and <hi>unſound things</hi> comprehended in the <hi>Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chiſm:</hi> And next, He aſſerts the
<hi>Author</hi> to be guilty of many <hi>Omiſſions;</hi> and this from one
pretending to Learning, who has diligently read and conſidered it, as he
ſays, is ſo inſignificant and idle Imputation, which all modeſt, and
ingenuous men, muſt never diſown; and that there are
<hi>Omiſſions,</hi> wilful and deſigned <hi>Omiſſions,</hi> I ſhall
never deny, for after it was firſt Compoſed, I did <hi>Compendize</hi> and
<hi>Abreviate</hi> it, ofter than once, to ſuit it to the Capacities of
ſuch for whom it was prepared, even young ones, to whom <hi>Quakers</hi> have
had little regard hitherto, as to their Inſtruction in Religious
Fundamentals: Neither have I ſeen any Writings of <hi>Quakers,</hi> even
thoſe pretending to give accounts of their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but juſtly may be
charged with greater <hi>Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> then any yet diſcovered in the
<hi>Catechiſm,</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>F. M.</hi> as the <hi>Doctrine</hi>
of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> in the <hi>God-head,</hi> the
<hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> the Pattern of all
Prayer; and <hi>George Fox</hi> his Received <hi>Catechiſm,</hi>
induſtriouſly ſpread by <hi>Quakers,</hi> not only ſavours of Humane
Learning, and words of mans wiſdom, but guilty of many weighty
<hi>Omiſſions,</hi> and fills up a great part with ſtuff wherein there is
no <hi>Religion;</hi> far leſs can they be called <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> as
<hi>Salutations</hi> by <hi>words</hi> 
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:171419:21"/>and <hi>Geſtures,
Covering</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncovering</hi> the Head, condemning Preaching in
<hi>Steeple Houſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Churches.</hi> Yea I appeal to the
impartial, and unbiaſſed Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> Compoſed by
<hi>F. M.</hi> contains not more of the Principles of Religion, then one
containing <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles, Compoſed by ſeveral Hands, as
<hi>Crook, Pennington, Burroughs, Parker, Smith,</hi> and ſeveral others; now
I refer my ſelf to every man, how invidious and unjuſt it is to Charge a
<hi>Catechiſm</hi> compoſed by one with <hi>Omiſſions,</hi> while ſo
many pretenders to immediate Revelations and Inſpirations, are guilty of ſo
great <hi>Omiſſions,</hi> and vain <hi>Repeticions,</hi> and there is not a
Book which I have ſeen writ by <hi>George Keith,</hi> but may as juſtly lie
under this Charge, as my <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> &amp; it were vain Oſtentation
to diſown it. And for my own part, I have ever obſerved in all the Writings
of men, Ignorance, Infirmity, and Imperfection, to magnifie the Excellency of
the Scriptures above all Books of mens Compoſure; but it is no ſtrange
thing to find <hi>Quakers</hi> quarrelling our ſuccinct way, of compoſing
our Principles for young ones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are oppoſite to ſo early
Edification, which practice is very inconſiſtent with Scripture Precepts,
and Preſidents of Training a Child when young, bringing up Children <hi>in
the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord;</hi> and <hi>Timothy knew the
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from a Child;</hi> and the advantage of an early Inſtruction is
witneſſed by the experiences of many Godly in all Ages, where attended with
the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, and purſued with Exhortation, until they arrive at
a riper age: Now I leave all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how inſignificant an imputation
this of <hi>Omiſſion</hi> is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171419:21"/>Another general Charge is, that I have not
declared from whence I have Received theſe things, and that I have owned in
the Title Page of my <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> to be but a Collection from others:
Theſe are heavy Charges with him, therefore ſhall anſwer them
particularly. 1. Any that reads his Paper, may underſtand he is as guilty of
that <hi>Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> as any of his Neighbours, for he has not told from
whence he had what is delivered in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and it was the beſt policy;
for he durſt not aſſert it was from the Spirit of God, becauſe of the
falſhood and malice it contains, as I ſhall make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. 2. If they are
the Truths of God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Scripture, it is eaſily determined from
whence theſe Truths are, which were queſtioned by few, until <hi>G. K.</hi>
whoſe Trade has been to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Contention, and ſtir up ſtrife in the
Churches of Chriſt in the World; and whoſe Arguments are ſo ſlender and
thred bare, that they ſcarce deſerve an Anſwer. 3. If I inclined to
ſtuff my Doctrines and Diſcourſe upon all occaſions, with enlarged
Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of Converſion or a work of Grace, with concomitant and conſequent
Experiences of the Operations of Gods Holy Spirit, as <hi>Keith</hi> pretends
to do, I might amuſe my Hearers; but Actions and Converſation are better
demonſtrations of a work of Grace, then all <hi>Keith's</hi> vain boaſting
Language, which with his ſelf magnifying Language, can be eſteemed nothing
elſe then a Crying up and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching himſelf, inſtead of Chriſt; for
though <hi>Paul</hi> oft declared his Converſion, and gloried in his
At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, it was, that the Free Grace of God might be exalted, and ſelf
abaſed; which <hi>Quakers</hi> are rarely acquainted with, either in Praying
or<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171419:22"/>Teaching, as many who have heard them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
declare.</p>
            <p>And becauſe <hi>Keith</hi> has ſhewn himſelf void of
Charity, by ſhooting his invidious Thunderbolt at a diſtance, e're he knew
or ſaw me, or I him, That I am infallibly a great ſtranger to the dealings
of Gods Spirit on the hearts of his People; I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to Juſtifie
my Office, from thoſe Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Calumnies, and that Grace might be
magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, by giving this Relation, in the ſight of an All ſeeing and
Omnipreſent God, that e're I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Impoſition of Hands, in that
Scriptural and Orderly Separation unto my Holy and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Calling, that
I gave requiring ſatisfaction to Godly, Learned, and Judicious Diſcerning
Men, of a work of Grace and Converſion wrought on my heart, at fifteen years
of Age, by, and from the pains of a Godly Schoolmaſter, who uſed no ſmall
diligence in Gaining Tender Souls to Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Fear; ſince which
time, to the Glory of his Free Grace be it ſpoke, I have had the ſure
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of Gods various Dealings with me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Infinite and
Unerring Wiſdom, to my unſpeakable comfort, whereby all may ſee how far
Grace is expected and deſired, with Gifts to qualifie for the Miniſterial
Office; for not only was this required of me, but is expected of all Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by Presbyters; which experience ſhall enable me not to value what
<hi>Keith,</hi> or any other <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhall ignorantly and
groundleſly affirm, in judging raſhly of my State, for we are looked upon
as of the World, and they only the People of God, as they commonly Cauterize
us; but this is our comfort, we ſhall not be Judged in the Laſt Day 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171419:22"/>by <hi>Quakers,</hi> who muſt as well as their
Neighbours, give an account of their raſh and uncharitable judgings to a
moſt Righteous Judge.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And that it is a Collection from the Scriptures of the
Living God, I never will deny, but glory in it; it <hi>Keith</hi> mean from
others, it is fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, and there is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o mention of thoſe others in the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Page; &amp; what hath
<hi>Keith</hi> Publiſhed in moſt of his Books, but Collections, and many of
them from the worſt of men, Hereticks long ſince conſured, with ſome
wild, ſophiſtical, and unſcriptural Notions of his own, both repugnant to
Scripture, and oppoſite to his Quaking Brethren: And 
<q>
                  <hi>Turpe est dectori eum cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pa redarguit ipſum.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He aſſerts, I declare not that it is God, or Chriſt, or the
Spirit of God, that convinceth or reproveth people of their ſins; but this is
ſo falſe a Calumny, that none in charity can judge <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith</hi> to be ſo great a
Perfectioniſt as he proclaims himſelf to be; and this every one may be
ſatisfied in, if they will but turn over to page 12 where it is plainly
delivered, That God in Turning or Calling Sinners unto himſelf, does
<hi>convince them of Sin and Miſery, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten their Minds with the
Knowledge of Chriſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news their wills,</hi> &amp;c. which is alſo the
judgment of all my Brethren, and particularly of thoſe of the
<hi>Westminſter</hi> Aſſembly, both in their Shorter and larger
Catechiſm. And whereas he charges me with this, that I mention but little of
the Spirit of God at all; and that this may appear as fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as the former, I refer my ſelf to every Reader, and
eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe who have read and conſidered, better then
<hi>Keith</hi> hath done; and let them turn over to the ſeveral pages, where
I have made frequent mention<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171419:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:171419:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:171419:24"/>of the Spirit of God, in ſo
ſmall a Volumn, aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to him that which was and is his peculia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work. 1. As being the Original Author,
and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diter of the Scriptures, <hi>page</hi> 3.2. As being one diſtinct from
the Father and the Son, <hi>page</hi> 4.3 O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt's revealing the <hi>Will of God to us, by Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Word and Spirit.</hi> page 10.4.
<hi>The Spirit of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> applies to us
the Redemption purchaſed by Chriſt,</hi> page 11.5. In the ſame page,
<hi>being the Author of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, or the New Birth,</hi> according to the
Scriptures, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>The Spirits ſanctifying of us,</hi> page
15.7. <hi>That he teaches us to pray aright, and acceptable to God,</hi> page
41. From hence every one may learn, what credit to give to <hi>Keith's</hi>
worth and Calumnies for the future; and though he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs my
Compaſſion over the tender Souls in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>American</hi> Deſart, to be a reflection againſt the
<hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi>
in <hi>Virginia,</hi> I am ſatisfied, it has n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> been ſo Received by them for whom it was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
neither judged ſo by the Spirit of God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> much after the ſame manner pitties and compaſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates <hi>the Ignorance of his own
people,</hi> by the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hoſ
4.6 <hi>My People are destroved for lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And I am
perſwaded, Quakers ſhould n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
have ſo great ſucceſs in drawing aſide ſilly Soul from the Truths and
Ways of God, if it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not for the
abounding Ignorance of <hi>Virginia,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other dark Corners of the World, who have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet received, and comprehended the Light ſhini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about them; and even their ignorance
of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fundamental Truths contained
in the Catech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> And none deſerves
more to be pitied for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, than Quakers, and of the moſt Fundame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Truths, notwithſtanding of their
high preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171419:24"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Spirit and Light
within, as <hi>John Drummond,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Reputed and Received Quaker, a
Reader of <hi>Keith</hi>'s Books, with many others, who lately at my Houſe at
<hi>Poccamok,</hi> before <hi>Keith</hi> and ſeveral other Witneſſes,
publiſhed his groſs Ignorance of that Fundamental Article, That none could
be Saved without Faith in Jeſus Chriſt; from which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſince,
that he had oft reproached me, drawing his own ignorant concluſions from
thence. And if Quakers are ignorant hereof, what can they pretend
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o know.</p>
            <p>Another general charge is, That I nothing help the Ignorant,
neither do I direct them to the true Viſion; but whoever will but conſider
how many Fundamental Truths are laid down in the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, for the
Edification of the Ignorant, and plainly aſſerted, That Chriſt teaches
his People with his Word and Spirit; and if this be not the true Viſion of
God, Quakers muſt loſe themſelves, and be puzzled in finding of it: but
he rather would inſinuate what harm it would do, if received; but this may
diſcover how far men are for keeping ſinners in ignorance, by
poſſeſſing their minds with a diſlike of this mean of Knowledge,
which leads and directs ſinners to the Scriptures as the great mean of
Knowledge, and profitable for inſtruction, containing all things
neceſſary to be known by Chriſtians; and alſo to Chriſt and his Holy
Spirit the Author and Efficient Cauſe of Knowledge, who can Enlighten without
means, in a moſt immediate manner, but moſt ordinarily conveyes Knowledge
by Means and Ordinances of his own Appointment concurring with his Holy Spirit,
bleſſing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them effectual to whom he pleaſes. And in 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171419:25"/>Catechiſm many ſavoury truths delivered, no fins
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged, moſt du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies relating
to our general and ſpecial callings enjoined: Now
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow the receiving ſuch a form of
ſound words containing poſitive Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, ſhould be prejudicial, and <hi>Kieth</hi>'s works
ſtuffed with <hi>Quibling,</hi> and <hi>Sophistical Controverſy,</hi> &amp;
his teachings filled with often repeated <hi>Calumny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> againſt all the Reformed Churches, and
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-ſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>unheard</hi> of
<hi>Long-winded Similitudes,</hi> which amuſe the deluded, and ignorant,
ſhould become profitable, let every one determine; and I am perſwaded, none
has received or can receive injury therefrom, but by ſlighting and
diſregarding it. And this my experience can teſtifie, that ſince the
Catechiſm was oppoſed by <hi>Quakers,</hi> they have had a more
univerſal, and kindly welcome, and recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And here is no new Doctrine,
but what <hi>Keith</hi> had oft ſeen in the Catechiſms of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
Churches, which he had oft impugned with all his might and Sophiſtry; and his
repeating his old Arguments, is only with vain Oſtentation, to ſhow
himſelf among a poor, ignorant, and deluded people, and once
poſſeſſing them with this, that what he delivers is immediately from
the Spirit of God, he may deliver what he will, as infallible, and never to be
queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Having anſwered his Generals, I proceed to examine his
particulars; and he ſuffers not the firſt page to paſs without a
Cenſure, becauſe I have affirmed, God made the World out of Nothing: and
that this is not only true, and agreeable to Scripture, that to word and
expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it otherwiſe, were
inconſiſtent with the Revelation of God, and it were to jump in with the
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171419:25"/>of Gods Truth, for we cannot conceive of
Creation, without ſaying it was made out of Nothing which all d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcribe to be, <hi>Preductio ex
nihilo;</hi> therefore as many places of Scripture as but mention Creation,
ſay as much as I have done, for which I am quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Did not Creation give
the Firſt Being to all things that were made, and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quently were all nothing before God commanded them to
be, for was not Light nothing till God ſaid, <hi>Let there be Light?</hi>
Further, if God made the World, he either made it out of his own Eſſence,
or ſome pre exiſtent matter from Eternity, or produced it out of nothing. I
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume you will not be ſo abſurd as to aſſert any of the firſt
two, not the firſt, for ſo the Eſſence of God ſhould become
diviſible and corruptible; not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, for then ſome matter ſhould
be Co-eternal with God, which were blaſphemy to affirm: And it is no ſmall
argument of the Omnipotence of God, to declare and affirm, eſpecially to
young ones, the World was made out of nothing, ſeeing they know not that it
is implied in the word Creation; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Omnipotent Power of God
in Creation, Acclamations of Praiſe are aſcribed to him, Pſal 33.6.
<hi>By the word of the Lord were the Heavens made, &amp; all the Host of them,
by the breath of his mouth,</hi> Acts 4.24, In that joynt Acclamation of the
Apoſtles, <hi>Lord thou art good, which haſt made Heaven, and Earth, and
the Sea, and all that in them is:</hi> And it is no adding to the Word of God,
while nothing is delivered but Gods Mind in his Word; though <hi>Keith</hi>
next in his pretences to <hi>Nailer</hi> himſelf ſhould diſcover ſo
much palpable weakneſs as to cenſure it again: And I have alſo
aſſerted in my Catechiſm, that there is no work ſo peculiar to any of
the Perſons of the Holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but all of them have a hand in each; ſo
that his<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171419:26"/>advice which he calls ſufficient, is prevented,
if he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diligently read and
conſidered it, as he has ſaid.</p>
            <p>In page 3. He chargeth me for mentioning no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teacher but the
Scriptures to direct us to Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and
Glorifie God; this is no ſtrange imputation fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quakers,</hi> who notwithſtanding of all their
fair preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet have uttered many vilipending expreſſion thereof,
calling it a dead Letter, a noſe of Wax, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> &amp; Ink Divinity; &amp; <hi>Keith</hi> in his publick
Teaching<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Accomack,</hi>
compared it to a Letter wrote from an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Husband to his Wife, which as
ſoon as he Return is to be laid aſide; any may eaſily apprehend wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Gentleman would be at, who alſo
in his Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> though he would make
fools believe he commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
Scriptures; yet immediately he accuſes it of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficiency, and
imperfection, and affirms there a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſeveral things which the Scriptures Teaches not,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which we muſt have immediate
Revelations; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Daniel
Acres,</hi> a Teacher in <hi>North Carolina,</hi> decla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to me, it bordered with Blaſphemy to call the
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the Word of God But he further affirms,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould have joyned the
Spirit of God and Chriſt with the Scriptures, and that I ſhould not only
hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done it, but that it is really
done, every Reader <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> find page
10 where it is taught, That Chriſt <hi>Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Will by his Word and Spirit;</hi> neither dare any
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſert, I have ſaid it was
only the Scriptures, exclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
Chriſt or the Holy Spirit of God; and yet we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ground from the Scriptures themſelves to affirm,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Scriptures are a rule to
which we are directed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the
Spirit of God, &amp; our Saviour too, and the ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and ſufficiency of the Scriptures for our direction,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſerted from the Spirit
of God, though we are u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous in
depending on the Bleſſing of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt, and concurrence
of his Holy Spirit<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171419:26"/>to make the Scriptures effectual to our
Salvation, with all other Means and Ordinances; yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are the
Rule for our Inſtruction and Direction, though Chriſt, and the Holy Spirit
of God the Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er up, and ſole Interpreter of the Scriptures to us, as all
of us Teach, Believe and Own; which is evident, from our Praying before and
after all our publick and private Adminiſtrations, which many
<hi>Quakers</hi> are abſolute ſtrangers to, as <hi>John Porter,</hi> of
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> River, who never was heard to Pray either before or after
Teaching; this Savours of <hi>Opus Operatum:</hi> I ſay, the Holy Spirit of
God endues us with skill to underſtand, apply and obey the Scriptures; ſo
that <hi>Quakers</hi> confound the Rule, with the skill in making uſe of that
Rule; but our judgment is fully delivered in anſwer to that Queſtion in the
Aſſemblies Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm. <hi>How is the Word made effectual to
Salvation;</hi> and that all that read theſe Sheets may ſee how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
it is to quarrel our Doctrine concerning the Scriptures, let them peruſe
thoſe following Scriptures; 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>All Scripture is given
by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for
Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for Instruction in Righteouſneſs;</hi> and in the foregoing
verſe, <hi>The Holy Scriptures which is able to make thee wiſe unto
Salvation, through Faith which is in Jeſus.</hi> 17 <hi>That the man of God
may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto every good work;</hi> and are we not
directed to the <hi>Law and to the Testimony,</hi> but no where directed to the
Light in all men, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the Heathen and Reprobate, to be our
Guide to Glory: Our Saviours advice favours and confirms our Judgment;
<hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them you think ye have Eternal Life, and they
are they that testifie of me.</hi> And we find our Lord in dealing with the
Capcious Jews, appealing to the Scriptures<pb n="32" facs="tcp:171419:27"/>as the Rule of
Faith, and Judge of Controverties, ſaying, It is written, and Cites the
Prophets oft for their Conviction, and charges them with ignorance of the
Scripture, as the cauſe and ground of their Error, ſaying, <hi>Ye Err, not
knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God</hi> And though dim Natures Light,
the Rellicks of one fallen from perfection, and the works of Creation, render
all inexcuſable for their Ignorance of their Creator, yet are very lame, and
inſufficient fully to teach their Duty, or to diſcove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all their ſins, or teach them the knowledge of God
and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, our Redeemer, whom <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> ſay is in
all men; but can this <hi>Jeſus</hi> of their be the true Chriſt, and
ſavingly in all men; ſeeing there are Nations and Kingdoms, who have not
the leaſt remote or dim notions of Chriſt the Son of God, as Saviour, or
Mediator between Sinners, and God, <hi>who was in Chriſt Reconciling the
World to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> and if ſo as <hi>Quakers</hi> affirm, then blinded
Paga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nations are in as brave a
caſe, as the Churches o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
Chriſt, to whom the Oracles of God are committed who are pronounced
bleſſed beyond all others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Gods Choſen Inheritance, and particularly from the great and tranſcending
priviledge of enjoying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Revealed Will of God, to whom the Divine Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were committed, and blinded
Nations were ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Predeceſſors,
within ſome few Centuries paſt.</p>
            <p>And what <hi>Keith</hi> underſtands by ſilent waiting
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, which he calls a
ſilence of mind and thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
I fear neither he, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any
<hi>Quaker</hi> for him, can ever demonſtrate from plain Scripture
Teſtimony; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is not the
firſt time they have been puzled to tell
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what it is, though ſome have
preferred it to the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the
Scriptures, and a Mean appointed,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, for right underſtanding
of the Scripture; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:171419:27"/>this new notion of theirs is warranted no where in the
Scripture; ſome of them have taken upon them to call it a ſilent poſture
of the heart, without think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good or evil; but this is ſo ſtrange a
conceit, that it is inconſiſtent with the nature of the heart and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of man, which is in the judgment of moſt, and ſolid experience of all, ſo
ſtirring and active a thing, that it is never at quiet or reſt, but always
employed about either good or evil, and this ſo many as call a Spirit <hi>Res
Gegitandi,</hi> ſay, is while man is aſleep; but further it is
inconſiſtent with Scripture waiting, for herein there muſt be an
exerciſe of the Graces of Faith, Patience, Hope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſal 4.1.
<hi>I waited pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for the Lord, and he enclined unto me, and heard my
Cry;</hi> here is both the exerciſe of Patience, and the uſe of Prayer, in
the Pſalmiſts ſucceſsful waiting, and how this can be without
exerciſing the heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout good or evil; this is much like the Commentary
and vulgar gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs of Quakers on
that Text, Mat. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. <hi>When thou
prayeſt, enter into thy Cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut the door,</hi>
or according to theſe able Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators,) <hi>ſhut thy heart,</hi> which
is an unfit frame for God, to whom we muſt open, and before whom we muſt
pour out our hearts Another Inſtance of Scripture waiting, very unlike
Quakers waiting you may find in Lam. 3 26. <hi>It is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that a man ſhould both hope and quietly wait for the
Salvation of the Lord;</hi> and let every one be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umpire in this caſe, whether
there can be the exerciſe of thoſe Graces, where the heart thinks neither
good nor evil; and they are often puzled to ſatisfie us, whether their
ſilent waiting be publick or private Worſhip; for if it is not done in
Faith, it muſt be ſin, and conſequently no acceptable Service to God; if
private or ſecret, it ought to be gone about with as great ſecrecy, and to
go too pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <pb n="34" facs="tcp:171419:28"/>with it, is viſible Hypocriſie to be
ſeen of men. If publick Worſhip, it muſt tend to the Edification of
others; but how the perfect ſilence, without all Admonition, Rebuke, Prayer,
Inſtruction, or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Praiſe edifies is unconceivable, and as
they meet, ſo they diſperſe oft, without the leaſt motion to ſpeak,
which demonſtrates how fruitleſs many ſuch Meetings are; and what they
amuſe the World with their imaginary experiences of refreſhments from their
ſilent Meeting, when nothing is ſaid, they muſt needs be like thoſe,
which an Engliſh Congregation received from a Quaking <hi>Dutch,</hi> woman,
Teaching in an unknown Language; and what reaſon we have of believing their
boaſted of Experiences from nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive imaginary Worſhip, and they regard
not the Experiences of thouſands of the Godly, of raviſhings of Soul, and
ineffable Joy and Comfort from Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God in ſinging of Pſalms, and
from Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating in the Supper of the Lord, as performed by us, and in
moſt of the Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>In the next place he condemns our aſſerting and believing
there are Three Perſons in the God head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is no wonder to find ſo
great and tranſcending a Myſtery, rather to be Reverenced, Adored, and
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, then Reaſoned and Diſputed, as it has been miſtaken and
quarrelled both by Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hereticks in the World. I encline not to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up the groſs Errors of
Ancient Hereticks concerning this Doctrine, as of <hi>Apollinarius, Arrius,
Rhofinus Neſtori us, Sabelius,</hi> and others, and am not a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> concerned, that Quakers pretending to
ſo great and ſo good things, ſhould joyn hand in hand with ſuch whoſe
ſubtilties have been long ſince cunningly ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and exploded; and
that they by their frequent and ſcurrilous Barkings againſt ſo
Fundamental <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:171419:28"/>Truth, as <hi>Solomon Acles,</hi> who in <hi>Barbadees</hi>
aſſerted this Doctrine to be a Presbyterian Fiction, and moſt others of
that Gang I have converſed with, had moſt ignorant, and groſs Notions of
a perſon, dreaming it to be ſome groſs, material, viſible and corporeal
Subſtance, like unto man, and looked upon it, an abſurdity to apply any
ſuch thing to God at all; and here I find one of their Learned and Litigious
Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, quarrelling Three Perſons in the God-head, or Divine Eſſence,
and how ſuch men can be Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led among themſelves, I leave to thoſe
that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; I muſt confeſs, if I underſtood what <hi>Keith</hi>
intends by this Charge ſo obſcurely delivered, I could with greater
fulneſs and particularity anſwer; and waving that uncharitableneſs he was
notoriouſly guilty of concerning me, and others, I conceive he only contends
about words, by calling Three Perſons in the God head, not Scripture
Language; but words of mans wiſdom, as all our Doctrines and Writings are
commonly Calumniated by ſuch. And this I muſt Animadvert the Reader, that I
am the more confirmed in that which I charged him with at my Houſe, that
moſt of his Writings are quibling Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, and his Debates a
diſputing about words, little to the Edification of Souls, but tending to
Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Diviſions in the Churches of Chriſt upon Earth of which he had been
a great Inſtrument already, by making perverſe Diſputings his Trade in
the World, and to confirm it, he brings a ſublime and tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Myſtery, rather to be adored and believed, then diſputed and brought under
the Debate of men of corrupt minds; but 1. If words not expreſſed in
Scriptures in the ſame Letters and Syllables, be words of mans wiſdom, and
an adding to the Scriptures, the Words of the Living God, then all
Expoſitions of<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171419:29"/>Scriptures, though agreeable to Scripture,
if not nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merically the ſame words, muſt be condemned and thruſt out of
doors; and then what will become of moſt of <hi>Keith</hi>'s Teachings, which
are delivered in publick as immediately from the Spirit of God, yet ſtuffed
to the amuſing rather than Edification of his Hearers, with unſcriptural,
unuſual, and unheard of Alluſions of a Key, and loſing and finding a Key,
as alſo of a Table and covering of a Tabling, with Trenchers and Napkins, and
a Cupboard at Home, and no Meat in it, as alſo a Husbands Writing Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to
his Wife, while abſent, all which was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Long winded
Diſcourſes at <hi>Thomas Fooks</hi> his Houſe in <hi>Onankok,</hi> and
<hi>Nuſswaddux,</hi> to numerous and mixed Auditories of men and women,
rather of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended then edified and affrighted from, then engaged to Quakers
Principles, or Practices. 2. If I ſhould make it appear, that Quakers are as
guilty of uſing words not to be found in the Scriptures, as any of their
Neighbours, will not all men believe them very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure others for that which they
practice themſelves, and conſequently from <hi>Keith</hi>'s words a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the words of the Scriptures; And 1.
Let any be prevailed with, to obſerve the Writing of this Litigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author,
which is filled in every page with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning, and Scholaſtick Notions,
making as much uſe of School Art in all his ſophiſtical Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,
as any that has put Pen to Paper, as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf owned the uſe of Humane Learning in all his Writings.
2 I ſhall inſtance to you from themſelves not only words, but ſentences
and phraſes, which none could ever yet find or hear of, in or from the
Scriptures, ſome whereof are <hi>Pens,</hi> others belong to
<hi>Barclay,</hi> others are uſual and common in the mouth of moſt Quakers,
as thoſe uncouch phraſes of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171419:29"/>in Spirit, which
<hi>Keith</hi> made uſe of at my Houſe; a meaſure of God, as if God were
divided in parcels, from the Spirit in Ward by ravening the Seed in Captivity
ravening comprehending brain, fleſhly comprehenſions, Traditional Read
Knowledge, Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous Eye, with many others; and for words none more new and
invented, without any foundation in the Scriptures, then ſome uſed by
Quakers; as Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle of the Spirit, Fermentation of the Spirit, and many ſuch
like. 3. How much is it to be Lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the frequent Debates, and
needleſs Janglings of <hi>Keith</hi> concerning this Subject, could not have
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed him; he muſt now upon his running Circuit, raiſe a new Debate,
and Controverſy, about words, which is Cenſured in the words of the Holy
Apoſtle, 1 Tim 6.4. <hi>He is proud knowing nothing, but doting about
Queſtions, and Strifes of words, whereby cometh Strifes, Railing, Evil
Surmiſings.</hi> 5. <hi>Perverſe Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of men of corrupt minds, and
deſtitute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that Gain is Godlineſs, from ſuch
turn away,</hi> or withdraw thy ſelf: And all ſuch are Cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the
words of Holy <hi>Calvin,</hi> that Eminent man of God, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. Cap.
13. The Hereticks bark at the name <hi>Perſon,</hi> and others too preciſe
Carp at all words deviſed by men, and would have all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain not only
their meanings, but their very words, ſtrictly within the bounds of
Scripture; who are be <hi>Calvin</hi> Charged as unreaſonable; who quarrel
words expreſſing nothing but what is teſtified and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by
Scripture, and what hinders, ſaith he, but we may in more plain words
expreſs ſuch things as are myſterious to ordinary Capacities, where there
are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary grounds urging thereunto? ſuch, ſaith he, as quarrel
this, muſt be reputed, to be grieved at the Light of the Truth, becauſe he
quarrels this, that the<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171419:30"/>Truth is made ſo eaſie &amp;
plain to be diſcerned; and the reaſon or ground given by this worthy
Author, why the Churches of Chriſt are neceſſitated to uſe ſuch
novelty of words, if they may be ſo called; is when the Truth is to be
Defended againſt Rangle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> who
deride it with Quibbles; ſo the Old Fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubled with Falſe
Doctrines, were neceſſitated to expreſs themſelves in exquiſite
plainneſs, leaſt they ſhould leave any crooked by ways to the wicked, to
whom the doubtful Conſtructions of words, were hiding Holes of Error;
therefore it was that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in Confutation of <hi>Arius,</hi> were
neceſſitated in aſſerting the Divinity of the Son, to call him
HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOUSION, or Conſubſtantial with the Father: And againſt
<hi>Sabellius,</hi> who denied all Diſtinction between the Father, Son, and
Holy Ghoſt, but what was Nominal; the Defenders of Truth were
neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſay, there did ſubſiſt in the Unity of God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Trinity of Perſons, which is moſt
ſuitable to, though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not rigidly
the ſame with the Language of <hi>John, There are Three, and theſe Three
are One</hi> Trinity, <hi>Tres <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nes,</hi> or <hi>Tres in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no,</hi>
Trinity.</p>
            <p>Having offered theſe Generals, I come particularly to the
Charge, for aſſerting there are Three Perſons in the God-head: All that
<hi>Keith</hi> would ſeem to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is only that it is not Scripture
Language; whereby he would ſeem to favour the great Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principle,
moſt of his Brethren have been blaſphemouſly barking againſt theſe
Thirty or Forty Years; and devoutly to ſay, There are Three in One: But it
were to be wiſhed, that he, and all of them, would demonſtrate themſelves
according to their uſual boaſting, more skilful in the Scriptures, then any
of their Neighbours, by declaring freely, &amp; ingenuouſly, what thoſe
Three are called, that are<pb n="39" facs="tcp:171419:30"/>but One God, and what
Subſtantive, they joyn with the Adjective three, which is diſtinguiſhed
in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; and then they would have dealt plainly
without all Popiſh Equivocation, or Reſervation; which all that Read their
Books, and frequently Converſe with them, will find the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of
Quakers as guilty of, as any ſubtile Jeſuit at St. <hi>Omers.</hi> For if
this great and Fundamental Truth, would be made plain to the Edification of the
Church of God, to which it is ſo highly neceſſary that God can neither be
known, believed in, or called upon aright without it, then ſome denomination
muſt be aſcribed, and given, differing from one another in Incommunicable
Properties; for they muſt either be three ſomethings, or three nothings;
the former being rejected, if three ſomethings, they muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three
Gods, three Eſſences, three Parts, of the ſame Eſſence, or three
Qualities, or three Names, or three Manners, or wayes of Subſiſting; To
aſſert to Three Gods, were inſufferable Blaſphemy: Though <hi>Joſiah
Coal</hi> is as guilty of as great Blaſphemy in a Letter to <hi>George
Fox,</hi> which as it came from a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, was alſo Approved of by
<hi>Pen</hi> himſelf, in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>John Faldo,</hi> a
Miniſter I lately ſaw in <hi>London;</hi> which for the Readers
ſatisfaction, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of all, I ſhall here Inſert.</p>
            <q>Dear <hi>George Fox,</hi> who art the Father of many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
whoſe Life has reached through us thy Children, even to the Iſles afar off;
to the Begetting of many again unto a Lively Hope; for which, Generations to
come, ſhall call thee Bleſsed; whoſe Being and Habitation is in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he powtr of the Higheſt, in
which thou Rules &amp; Governs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n
Righteouſneſs: And thy Kingdom is Eſtabliſhed in Peace, and the
Encreaſe thereof is without End.</q>
            <p>Let <hi>Pen,</hi> and as many as will dare to Juſtifie this, 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:171419:31"/>conſider the Language of the Righteous God: <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Justifies the Wicked, and he that
Condemneth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Juſt, even they
both are Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return, To aſſert Three Eſſences, were to conceal
Three Eſſentially Diſtinct, which were to fall in with the former
abſurdity: To receive or be lieve three parts of the ſame Eſſence, or
God head which were moſt inconſiſtent with that Oneneſs and abſolute
Simplicity in the Nature of God, which cannot be conceived diviſible; and to
call the three in one, three qualities or accidents, were to believe accidents
in God, which were abſurd; and to aſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> nothing elſe but three Names, were to fall in with the long
ſince exploded Hereſy of <hi>Apollinarius,</hi> and to hold Faith repugnant
to the Rule of Gods Word whence he has twice Three Names, and yet aſſerted
to be but Three only; ſo that it muſt be Three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Manners,
Methods, or Wayes of Subſiſting, and is Termed in the Schools,
<hi>Ens,</hi> and <hi>Modus En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> And according to the unanimous Opinion
of our Reforming and Reformed Divines: A Perſon in the God-head, is whole
God, not abſolutely or ſimply conſidered, but by way of ſome perſonal
Properties or a manner of Being, or Diſtinct Subſiſtence, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
whole God-head in it. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> call a Divine
Perſon, a Subſiſtence in the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which having relation to the
other, is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from them, with Incommunicable Properties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So
that though the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be really and eſſentially
the ſame in Eſſence or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet they have ſomething differing from
one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for if the <hi>Word, Joh.</hi> 1.1. had been ſimply, and
abſolutely God without any thing peculiar to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, it had been improper,
and amiſs to have ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
was not only God, but with God. To which D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine<pb n="41" facs="tcp:171419:31"/>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> agrees,
ſaying, there is in God a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diſpoſition, or Diſtribution, which
changeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Unity of the Eſſence. I need not heap up theſe
manifold Teſtimo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies both of old,
&amp; New Teſtament, aſſerting Three in One, and One in Three; and if any
quarrel the word perſon, they ſhall find this plain Scripture Language,
<hi>Heb</hi> 1.3. ſpeaking of Chriſt the Second Perſon in the Trinity;
ſaith, <hi>He is the Brightneſs of his Fathers Glory; and Expreſs Image
of his Perſon,</hi> can any ſerious, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated Reader paſs over
this Text, without own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word Perſon, to be Scripture Language, and
that the Father is a Perſon, diſtinct in Perſon from God the Son; for he
is not called the Fathers Perſon, Remark it Reader, but the <hi>Expreſs
Image of his Fathers Perſon:</hi> And if none muſt be called a Perſon,
but the Father, as ſome Quakers have ſaid, then what was Chriſt's
Perſon, when Mediator, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Natures of God and man, not mans
perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality, for ſo Divine Nature would have ſatisfied in the Perſon
of the Humane Nature, which would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply no ſmall Abſurdities, or he
ſhould be the Perſon of the Father, which were repugnant to the formerly
cited Text: Our Mediator was without all Perſon. And finally, if the Father
is a Perſon, and the Son the Image of this Perſon, why not the Holy Ghoſt
a Perſon alſo, and Three in One, and One in Three</p>
            <p>The Next Charge is, and that a Weighty one in P. 9, &amp; 10. And
that is for mentioning only Three Offices of Chriſt, as Mediatour, a
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Priest,</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> And that <hi>Really,
Savingly,</hi> and only to thoſe that <hi>Believe</hi> in him, and to whom
<hi>He is Actually a Saviour;</hi> and that thoſe Three Offices include,
<hi>All that Chriſt did,</hi> and was <hi>Reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be done</hi> as
<hi>Mediatour;</hi> None, even <hi>Kieth</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:171419:32"/>himſelf
cannot deny, as he readily owned at my Houſe, all was Reducible to thoſe
Three Offices, which are all we have mentioned in the Scriptures, and thoſe
Three. are very Obvious and Plain.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is called, and that Deſervedly, <hi>The Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prophet of His Church,</hi> according
to that Promiſe of, and Prophecy concerning him; <hi>A Prophet ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord your God raiſe up unto you,
like unto hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Brethren, Him ſhall
ye hear in all things.</hi> And thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Promiſe was fulfilled in his Coming, and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this his
Prophetical Office, by being the <hi>Great Goſpel-Preacher to his Church, and
People; Declaring the Way, and Means of Salvation, by a Mediatour, delivering
the Will of His Father;</hi> This was Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied alſo of him in
<hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3. and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.1. <hi>He is called, the
Apoſtle of our Profeſſion. And He is the Sole Teacher of the Mysterys of
Salvation from the Father.</hi> Matth. 11.27 <hi>No Man knoweth the Father
ſave the Son, and he to whom ſoever the Son will reveal him.</hi> And this
Our Great Prophet do's not always immediately, elſe <hi>K</hi>'s. Teachings
and all the Teachings among <hi>Quakers,</hi> were moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and
vain, but,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By the Holy Scriptures, Profitable for Doctrine, and able
to make the Man of God, Wiſe unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By His Meſſengers, and Miniſters, whom he has
commanded to <hi>Go, and Teach all Nations;</hi> and ſent to give Warning to
His Churches, and People, Therefore from their Office, and Teaching, called
Teachers.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, by his Holy Spirit in the Hearts of his People,
where Chriſt dwells not Subſtantially, as <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay, but
Spiritually by Faith; and ſo is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited by Faith tho' Locally Diſtant,
without the<pb n="43" facs="tcp:171419:32"/>Preſence of the things United, as <hi>K.</hi>
would inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and aſſert in his Paper. For if there can be a Moral
Union, and Relation ſtanding firm betwixt a Husband, and Wife, the one in
<hi>Europe,</hi> the other in <hi>America,</hi> and a Natural Union, and nigh
Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, between Parent, and Child, much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt in Heaven,
and believers on Earth, by a Spiritual, and indiſſolvible Union, by Faith,
which is not an abſent Chriſt to Believers, with whom he is by Gracious,
and Spiritual Influences in their Hearts; And <hi>K</hi>'s. Subtle, and
Sophiſtical Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the General, and Univerſal Preſence of
Chriſt as God, to his ſpecial and Gracious Preſence as Mediatour, will
take Place with none, but Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and Deluded <hi>Quakers;</hi> for ſo the
Devils in Hell, ſhould enjoy as great a Priviledge as Believers on Earth.</p>
            <p>And alſo it is granted that he is the Eternal High-Prieſt of
His Church, who Offered and gave Himſelf a Sacrifice once upon the Croſs
for Sinners and by the Efficacious Merits of this Death, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Perſons
and Services of his People accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God, not only Teaching them by His
Holy Spirit, what to pray for as they ought; but alſo continues <hi>an
High-Prieſt at the Right-hand of God, making continual Interceſſion for
Believers, Heb.</hi> 7 15. <hi>Wherefore he is able to Save them to the
uttermost, that come to God by Him, ſeeing he ever Liveth to make
Interceſſion for us;</hi> all which is fully and ſoundly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in
the Catechiſms, and Confeſſions of Faith of our Divines of the
<hi>Weſtminster</hi> Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, He is the Sole King, Head and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver of his
Church; by which Kingly Power, and Authority, he Appoints Laws and Statutes,
for the Counſel and Direction of his people, even to the 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:171419:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:171419:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:171419:34"/>binding of Conſcience, with the whole inward man, in whom
Chriſt does Rule, and Reign, even in and over ſuch as ſubject their Souls
to his Government, ſuffering Chriſt to Reign over them</p>
            <p n="2">2 He Subdues and Conquers ſinners Naturally Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to
himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, making them from an
Un-willing, a Willing People, in the Day of his power.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In defending of his Church from all their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
aſſuring them, the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 He reſtrains the Fury, and rage of, and Fina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
executes his Wrath on all His, and their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys.</p>
            <p>And we never did diſown that the ſpecial Fruits of all theſe
Three Offices are wrought in the heart of Believers; which is inconſiſtent
with that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Prieſt, &amp; King</hi> in all men according to
<hi>Quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Doctrine, while the
Scripture affirms, they are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, in whom Chriſt is not. And it is
plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Quakers</hi> common
Chriſt, is not the true Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and Meſſiah, who only dwells in the
hearts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Believers by Faith, and
not of Infidels that do not ſo much as know by any kind of knowledge, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yet they are Enlightned by him, as
they ſay, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficient,
and ſaving knowledge. How unneceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> muſt it be to multiply Offices in our Mediatou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeeing all are reducible to thoſe
Three? and muſt he not be a Man of a Perverſe Spirit, and contentio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mind, that would raiſe a Debate upon
this head and <hi>K</hi>'s Evaſion and Quibble for this is extreem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſilly, and weak; for (ſaith he)
the Commands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods Moral Law
are reducible to two; yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
branched out into Ten; for the firſt Diviſion
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Divine Commands, was by
God himſelf into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tables or two
Commands; yet the ſame G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:171419:34"/>makes the Enumeration or Diviſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to
ten; but no ſuch Warrant can be produced for this Enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or
Multiplication of Offices in our Mediator; for it were as impertinent, and
idle, as if every Duty required, and every Sin prohibited in every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
were a new Command; and there ſhould be thrice ten inſtead of ten; and what
muſt be thought of thoſe that multiply Offices in Chriſt, calling every
thing that Chriſt is called a new Office in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, as a
<hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> an <hi>Husband, Phyſician, &amp;c.</hi>
Whence he is called the <hi>Way,</hi> a <hi>Rock,</hi> a <hi>Door,</hi> a
<hi>Vine;</hi> all which denote no new Offices, but ſignifie his Richneſs,
Fulneſs, Benefits, Love and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Believers, denoting that Spiritual
Relation to Believers, and Chriſt's uſefulneſs to them in all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates
and Conditions.</p>
            <p>His next Charge, Page 10, 11. I have affirmed Chriſt Died, or
was Sacrificed for Sinners. Now let any determine whether this Anſwer does
not ſet forth the Fruit, and Satisfaction of Chriſt's Death for Sinners;
for if he Died for Sinners, and for our Sins, is it not enough to us; for if we
had not been Sinners, we ſhould not have ſtood in need of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: and
if ſinners were Redeemed, no others did want it. And tho' he ſeems to
reprehend it with Scripture Language, yet his Charge is more obſcure, and
defective, then that he finds fault with; either that quarrelled at muſt be
true, or falſe, or deficient; if true, why Cenſured, if falſe, let
Quakers ſpeak their minds plainly; if deficient, there muſt be ſome for
whom Chriſt Died, beſides Sinners. If I have not multiplied words, to
humour captious and critical Quakers, I hope I ſhall never have cauſe to
repent it, where I Studiouſly avoided all prolixity, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured all
ſuccinctneſs and brevity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:171419:35"/>But to return to the matter in hand concerning
the Nature, Efficacy, and Extent of Chriſt's Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we have to do with
many Adverſaries, whoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sentiments are not to be reconciled either
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, or with the Holy Scriptures: for ſome ſay, Chriſt
Died abſolutely for all, and every individual ſinner, and in Laying down
his Life, did equally intend the Salvation of all; others ſay, he Died for
all conditionally, from a foreſeen condition of Faith; ſo it was only a
conditional Salvation, or Redemption, wherein not one was abſolutely
Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; this by ſome is called a poſſible Salvation; whereby they
explain Univerſal Redemption to be nothing elſe, then Chriſt's Pacifying
an Angry God for all, and leaving all in a poſſibility of Salvation if they
will; others of a middle ſort, ſay, he Died abſolutely for the Elect of
God, but conditionally for the Reprobate: But the moſt unanimous, and
received Doctrine of the Reformed Churches, is, That whom Chriſt Died for, he
abſolutely and compleatly Redeemed; and that was ſome Select and Choſen
Number, given him <hi>of God the Father,</hi> to Lay down his Life for them, as
our Lord himſelf hints plainly to us in John 17. at large, of which ſays
he, <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> was Leſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I may diſcover the abſurdities of the former Opinion;
conſider firſt, Chriſt's abſolute Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for all, and every
individual Sinner: For 1. So <hi>Christ</hi> ſhould have intended to have
ſaved thoſe that were actually in Hell, and condemned to Eternal Flames,
before his Death, under an Irrevocable Sentence of Wrath. 2. What a Diſhonour
were it to God to ſay, he intended, and at ſo dear a rate, as the Death of
his own Son, to go about the Redeeming of thoſe whom he knew from all
Eternity ſhould be infallibly<pb n="47" facs="tcp:171419:35"/>Damned; can it be imagined,
<hi>Chriſt</hi> intended to Save ſue? 3. If all men and women, were
abſolutely Redeemed, all ſhould be infallibly Saved, for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
ſuppoſes Redemption, and Redemption ſecures Salvation; but it is evident
to all, the ſmalleſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall <hi>Enter in at the Strait Gate</hi>
4. If God ſhould purpoſe and intend the Salvation of all abſolutely, and
yet the ſmalleſt number eſcape Eternal Wrath, what ſhould the
purpoſes and intentions of God be more then the purpoſes, and intentions of
his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that can be fruſtrated, diſappointed and come to nought?</p>
            <p>Let us view the abſurdities and inconſiſtencies that flow
naturally from the univerſal, cnuditional Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, whereby all are left
under a poſſibility of Salvation, if they will; and 1. If ſo, then it
would have been poſſible, for all to have been Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and not one Saved;
for if man had but reſiſted as it was in his Power, becauſe not
abſolutely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, then Chriſt might have Died really for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and
have ſeen no Fruit of <hi>the Travait of his Soul:</hi> And, let ſerious
Souls conſider what an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant Death, and fruitleſs inefficacious
Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption ſhould he have Paid. 2. If a conditional Redemption, and a
poſſibility of Salvation was all that Chriſt Died for, I would Enquire,
Who it is that performs the Condition, God or man; if men can believe or repent
of themſelves, then the Conditional Salvation, might avail them ſomething;
but he cannot believe, it is Gods ſpecial Gift, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. And man
cannot repent, for it is his grant, 2 <hi>Tim</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 What will a Poſſibility of Salvation for all men
avail, and a conditional Redemption ſignifie, if all men are not left alſo
in a Poſſibility of believing and Repenting alſo, if, and when they
would.<pb n="48" facs="tcp:171419:36"/>3. If a conditional Univerſal Redemption, be all
the Redemption accompliſhed by Chriſt, then it is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for
man to be ſaved, as if he had not bee Redeemed at all; ſeeing it is as
impoſſible for ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to perform
the Conditions, as it is for him to redee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf; and all may ſee if this be <hi>Quakers</hi> un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verſal Redemption, what a poor,
lame, ineffectua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and half
Redemption they believe in, and build upon for their Salvation; as
<hi>Barclay</hi> has declared, in Publiſhing his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal
Redemption,</hi> ſufficiently confuted, by Mr. <hi>Brown;</hi> not anſwered
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he was Removed off the Stage,
by Death.</p>
            <p>And ſuch as tread the middle path, holding an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abſolute, Redemption of Gods Elect,
and only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Conditional
Salvation of the Reprobate; They hold (1.) A Twofold manner of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which we have no ground for in the Scriptures all that are Redeemed, being
Redeemed alike.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If ſo, the greateſt part of Mankind are left in as bad
a ſtate, as if they were not Redeemed at all.</p>
            <p>If we conſider the Merit of Chriſts Crucifixion and Death,
materially in regard of its Sufficiency, Dignity, Worth, and Merit, by
Reflecting on the Perſon who Suffered and Died, and of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how he
Accompliſhed it, with Faithfulneſs, and that moſt Willingly, and
Chearfully, that it was no leſs Price then the Death of him, who was God,
Equal with God the Father; The Ranſome muſt be owned, and believed, of
Infinite Value, and Worth, Merit, and Dignity, and ſo not only a compleat,
and ſufficient Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the ſins of the whole World, but was in
it ſelf a compleat Ranſome, for the Offences of a Thouſand Worlds. And
ſo if we conſider<pb n="49" facs="tcp:171419:36"/>the Sufficiency of his Price, and
Ranſome, he Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all, he Offered a Sacrifice, and gave an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement
that was enough for all, he gave himſelf a Ranſome for all, and Taſted
Death for every man; further we aſſert, and believe, that all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
Kingdoms, Tongues, and People were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by Jeſus Chriſt; ſo
according to the School diſtinction, He Dyed, for, <hi>Generibus
Singulorum,</hi> for, <hi>All kinds of men,</hi> not for <hi>Singulis
Generum,</hi> not for, <hi>Every Individual Man and Woman</hi> according to
<hi>Johns</hi> Viſion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. <hi>For thou waſt ſtain, and
haſt Redeemed us to God, by thy Blood, out of every Kindred, and Tongue, and
People, and Nation, ſo that all</hi> and every one that is or ſhall be
Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are Redeemed by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the only Saviour, and
<hi>no Name given under Heaven where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we can be Saved, but by the Name
Jeſus;</hi> ſo he is the Saviour of all. And this we dare moſt bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
and Warrantably affirm, that Chriſts Death is Efficacious for the Salvation
of all, whom he died for, and not one of theſe Predeſtinated to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Life, ſhall Periſh, but be brought Infallibly to Glory; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.
<hi>Whom he did Predeſtinate them he alſo Called, and whom he Called, them
he alſo Juſtified, and whom he Juſtified, them he alſo Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
From which Scripture, none can be Ignorant, unleſs they wilfully ſtop, and
Blind the Eyes of their underſtandings, what an inſeperable connecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is
between the Means, and the End, and all flowing from the Everlaſting
Purpoſe, and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Predeſtination of God; and as many as Chriſt Died
for, ſhall be infallibly Saved, and to whomſoever he has purchaſed
Salvation, to as many he has Purchaſed all the Means and Conditions, of
Salvation, as Faith, Repentance, and all the<pb n="50" facs="tcp:171419:37"/>Holy Graces of
the Spirit of God; for ſaith the Spirit of God, as many as were ordained to
<hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, Believed;</hi> neither dare we believe ſuch an ineffectual
Redemption, as <hi>Quakers</hi> hand in hand with <hi>Arminians,</hi> and
<hi>Pelagians</hi> do hold, which only leaves man in a poſſibility of
Salvation, if the ſinner will; but may be, the moſt of Chriſts Redeemed
ones, go to Hell notwithſtanding; while Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17. Speaks of
his Redeemed and Ranſomed ones, <hi>as thoſe Select Ones, whom the Father
had given him out of the World, for whom, that is the World, He would not ſo
much as Pray, far leſs dye;</hi> and <hi>Keith</hi> himſelf owns in his
Malicious Uncharitable Book, <hi>Against New-England Miniſters,</hi> that
there are thoſe for whom it may be ſaid, Chriſt <hi>Dyed not.</hi> And
ſo this muſt be the Gentlemans <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Chriſt dyed for all, and
dyed not for all;</hi> which is a plain conradiction; and farewel
<hi>Keith</hi>'s uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Redemption, which if it had not evaniſhed in a
contradiction, was uncomfortable, and ineffectual to the greateſt number of
Redeemed ones.</p>
            <p>I Remember in the beginning <hi>Keith</hi> ſays, <hi>I ſpeak
very little of the Spirit of God at all,</hi> which I have already ſhown in
the moſt convincing, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular manner to be Falſe, by directing the
Reader to the particular Pages, and now I am to ſhow he contradicteth
himſelf, by owning in ſeveral Queſtions, and Anſwers, my aſſerting,
<hi>The Spirits Operations, in calling Effectually, in Regeneration, in Working
Faith in us, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting us to Christ?</hi> But while he is neceſſitated
to own this; He affirms it, <hi>To be inconſistent with, and contradictory
to, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and</hi> My Brethrens
Doctrine; <hi>which he endeavours to confirm, by a far fetched, and
inconſequential reaſon,</hi> becauſe we deny <hi>all extraordinary
immediate, and<pb n="51" facs="tcp:171419:37"/>Objective Revelation,</hi> ſuch as the
Apoſtles had; and tho' we diſown this Doctrine of theirs, how it ſhall
Follow, we renounce, all the ſpecial Gracious, and ſaving operations of the
Spirit <hi>of</hi> God, in and by the uſe <hi>of</hi> means, and Ordinances
<hi>of</hi> Gods own appointment, and ſometimes immediately, where External
means of our Salvation are Wanting; in the Regeneration, Sanctification of
Souls, &amp; in making them meet <hi>for</hi> himſelf in Glory; I leave both
to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Gracious Souls to Determine.</p>
            <p>But every Chriſtian Reader may diſcover, in this perſon, a
moſt Arrogant Spirit, to pretend to know my Principles, and Opinions better
than I know them my ſelf, and with impudent falſhood, to affirm and
declare, I have Publiſhed an Account of Principles I do not believe; and that
they are repugnant to my Brethrens Doctrine; ſeeing our publick
Confeſſions of Faith, and Catechiſms known to the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
World, ſayes the ſame things, and particularly in the Deſcription of
Effectual Calling, which is further confirmed in all our common places, and
Bodies of Divinity, and in all the practical Pieces, treating of theſe
Subjects, as Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> of Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> and
Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> of Regeneration, and many others; and I am ſatisfied, how
oft I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in publick my Opinion in theſe matters. I muſt needs
declare, it is an evil Principle, and unfair Undertaking for any to take upon
them to Publiſh Principles, and contradict Principles, of thoſe he is an
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſolute ſtranger unto; and it
is the true Character of a Deceiver, to poſſeſs others with prejudices
againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Principles, only by
miſrepreſenting of them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtening Principles on us, which we abhor. And
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to all inward Revelation, or
ſpeaking of God to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Souls and
Hearts of Believers, I never read nor<pb n="52" facs="tcp:171419:38"/>heard of any of our
Divines, abſolutely deny or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: And I have upon all occaſions, publickly Taught, and Do, and
ſhall in the Strength of Jeſus Chriſt, firmly believe, and that unto the
end, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminating, Sanctifying, Mortifying, Quickning O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations <hi>of
the Holy Spirit of God,</hi> in the hearts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſound Believer, in
reſtoring the Corrupted Soul to the Forfeited Image of God; ſo it is
evident, how inclinable <hi>Keith</hi> is to Calumniate, and miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
us, upon all occaſions. How great muſt the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of Quakers needs be,
who cannot, or their perverſneſs be that will not, diſtinguiſh between
Enthuſiaſtick, Immediate, Extraordinary and Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Revelations; from
the Spirits Gracious and Sp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Illumination of his mind, impreſſing
thoſe Truths made known, and Revealed in an ordinary way, by Means of Heavens
Appointment; giving them Efficacious Grace to ſee, Embrace, Cloſe with, and
make Saving Application of them to their heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Grace to obſerve the ſame in their Lives; which ordinary
and extaordinary Operations they confound together, as they do the Univerſal,
or General <hi>Preſence of Christ,</hi> with his ſpecial, ſaving, and
gracious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, holding him to be in all, after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And
whereas he has aſſumed boldneſs to affirm, we call it Blaſphemy to
ſay, Chriſt is really in the Saints. All the Anſwer this deſerves, is,
that it is Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Falſe, and a groundleſs Calumny; For all of us
firmly believe, <hi>That unleſs the Spirit of Chriſt be in us, we are none
of his; and Chriſt is in us, except we be Reprobate,</hi> and he dwells in
all Believers; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from
<hi>Pauls</hi> words, it is by Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> declared, and that fully from
that Text, Coloſ. 1.27. <hi>Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory.</hi> And it is
no contradiction to affirm, and believe that God hath<pb n="53" facs="tcp:171419:38"/>called
Sinners out of Sin, unto Grace, yet at the ſame time to feel, and aſſert,
that all have ſin remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them; for it is no hard matter to
diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt Sinners being under the Power, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and Slavery,
or Drudgery of Sin; and a Sinners having ſome Relicks and Remainders of Sin,
and Corruption in them, whereby even in Believers there is a conſtant and
ſpiritual Warfare raiſed in the believing Soul, whereas formerly the Strong
Man kept the Houſe, the Apoſtle gives us this diſtinction; <hi>Sin
ſhall not have Dominion over you, you are not under the Law, but under
Grace;</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle, even after his Converſion, complains of
his own ſinful, wretched Corruption, and at the ſame time Triumphs in the
Victory obtained, for in the next breath; <hi>Thanks be to God who has given us
the victory;</hi> and if Sin in ſome meaſure be not cotemporary with
ſaving Grace, or Converſion, what muſt become of <hi>Quakers</hi>
univerſal ſufficient, and ſaving Grace, and all the multitudes of them, I
have ever ſeen, muſt according to their own Opinion, be void of
Converſion, Grace and Juſtification; for Sin have been eaſily
diſcernable in all, neither did ever any of them produce one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for
their abſolute perfection; and yet none of us aſſert, that the Saints
Sincerity, Thought, Word and Deed, as <hi>Keith</hi> falſely words it; yet it
ſtrictly, and ſpiritually taken; all are attended with Infirmities. I am
quarrelled, for aſſerting in my Catechiſm, page 25. This Juſtification
and Adoption, are Acts of God, without us, and and work only a relative Change;
and that Juſtification, Adoption and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification once had cannot be
Loſt. As to the firſt, Juſtification is according to the Judgment of all
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtant Divines, a gracious
Act of Gods Love, in a<pb n="54" facs="tcp:171419:39"/>Judicial Way, upon the account of
Chriſt's Imputed Righteouſneſs, acquitting, and abſolving the ſinner
from Guilt, and conſequently from Condemnation. I hope <hi>Quakers</hi> will
not jump in with Papiſts, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
aſſert, Juſtification to be the making of one Juſt, and ſo Confound
it with Sanctification, which the Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of God makes to be diſtinct Acts, tho' always unſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. As
to Adoption in its nature, it is God Numbering us among his Children, a taking
us from among the Children of Satan, and <hi>Giving us a Right to all the
Priviledges of Gods Children;</hi> &amp; pray where is the falſhood, and
danger, in aſſerting, they are Acts of God without us, bringing Believers
into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> new Relation unto God,
Chriſt, and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to whom they are Enemies and Strangers by
Nature; ſeeing at the ſame time we firmly believe, that there is no
Relative Change wrought by God on any Sinner, in Juſtification or Adoption,
without a real, ſaving, inward, gracious, and univerſal Change upon the
whole man by Sanctification, which are as different by the Language of the
Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as Sanctification and Glorification is, Rom. 8. And
none are Juſtified or Adopted, but <hi>Sanctified</hi> alſo; all which is
aſſerted in my Catechiſm; if <hi>Keith's</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, Cavelling,
and Carping Spirit had allowed him to take notice thereof; for none of us hold,
that God makes any his people, or children, without a real, gracious
<hi>Change,</hi> as <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Keith</hi> would invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duouſly and
falſely Calumniate us, and our univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known Doctrine, fairly
publiſhed to the World; and yet that renewing work is not properly
Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but Sanctification, which is a gradual work; whereby the Old
man of ſin and corruption, <hi>is Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfyed, and the New man of Grace,
Righteouſneſs or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, is rrnewed and put on, more and more;</hi>
and<pb n="55" facs="tcp:171419:39"/>though <hi>Keith</hi> would make Peace of Conſcience
to be the Eſſence, and Nature of Juſtification; yet all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Divines, with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> make it a concomitant, or rather a
conſequent Bleſſing to our Juſtification, Rom 5.1. <hi>Being
Juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God.</hi> And whoever denied
Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to work a real change, which my Catechiſm plainly aſſerts.
And that Juſtification, Adoption and Sanctification may be Loſt, is not
only the Doctrine of <hi>Quakers,</hi> but of <hi>Pelagians, Papiſts</hi> and
<hi>Arminians</hi> too; though <hi>Keith</hi> and <hi>Barclay</hi> own that
ſome may Arrive to ſuch a pitch and meaſure that they cannot <hi>Fall
away;</hi> now this meaſure muſt either be higher than Juſtification,
Sanctification, or Regeneration, or they contradict themſelves, in oppoſing
Free Grace, and denying the Perſeverance of the Saints in Grace with moſt
diſcouraging and comfortleſs arguments to Believers, which imply many
groſs abſurdities; and concerning this Head, Mr. <hi>John Brown</hi> our
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try man, in confutation of <hi>Barclay,</hi> layes down our unanimous
Doctrine, and firſt animadverts all that we hold, the Perſeverance of none,
but ſuch as are Regenerated; and how falſe and abſurd were it to ſay, a
Sinner Regenerated, or made a Child of God to Day, and yet be a Child of the
Devil to morrow, made meet for Heaven, and yet go to Hell, Pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and yet
Damned. 2. We do not hold a ſpecial and inevitable neceſſity of
Perſeverance, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, and lying in Sin, as Enemies would
inſinuate to the prejudice of Truth, as <hi>Quakers</hi> often have done. 3.
We do not maintain a Perſeverance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on the will of man, but on the
gracious Covenant, <hi>The Everlasting Purpoſe of God,</hi> the
Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſs of his Love, and Efficaciouſneſs of Chriſt's
Death.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:171419:40"/>4 That a Believer may fall away,
Back-ſlide and Depart from God by many degrees, as, (1) From Duty, as
Hearing, Reading, Praving, Praiſing <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (2) Into Grievous Sins,
as <hi>Noah, David, Soloman,</hi> and <hi>Peter.</hi> (3) Inro great Doubts,
and Fears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out their State. (4)
From Degrees of Grace, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom a
Strong unto a Weakneſs of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Zeal for God, and Religion, may grow ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cold, they may fall
from their <hi>Firſt Love;</hi> they may fall from their former meaſure of
Fear. And (5) they may Fall from the Truth of the Goſpel, from the Doctrine
of Our Lord Jeſus, and embrace many groſs, and dangerous Errors, and
<hi>Believe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye.</hi> (6) They
may fall from the Accidentals of their Gracious State, as Senſe of Favour,
Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Gods <hi>Love,</hi> Strength of Habits, Meaſures of
Comfort, is oft times and may be remitted, and loſt. And yet in the laſt
place, we Believe mentain and hold, <hi>There can be no Total and Final
Apostacy, and Defection from a Regenerate State, or the Eſsence, and Habits
of all Grace, and this is not only our Doctrine, but the Doctrine of all our
Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es:</hi> tho' <hi>K</hi>'s Invidious Malice is moſt commonly
ſet againſt the Reformed Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> verifying the Ancient
and common ſaying, <hi>Omnis Apostate ſua Secte oſor.</hi> And every
ſerious ſoul may eaſily conceive how comfortleſs, and diſcouraging
the Doctrine of <hi>Quakers</hi> muſt needs be, to all <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated,</hi>
and <hi>Believing</hi> Souls; if after <hi>Regeneration,</hi> being in Covenant
with God, Sealed with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe, Redeemed with the Blood of
Jeſus, they may yet be Damned in the End, this, and many more are the
Abſurdities that attend this Ancient <hi>Pelagian,</hi> and <hi>Arminian
Error,</hi> as [1] Is it not inconſiſtent with that Puffing up Doctrine 
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:171419:40"/>of their Perfection, they could never yet demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
from inſtances. [2.] It is inconſiſtent with the Immutability of Gods
Love, <hi>for whom He Loves He Loves unto the end,</hi> for his Gracious
purpoſes, are Unalterable, and his Will Irreſiſtible, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
4.1.31. <hi>They that wait on the Lord, ſhall renew their Strength, they
ſhall mount up with Wings, as</hi> Eagles <hi>they ſhall run, and not be
weary, and they ſhall walk and not be Faint.</hi> [3] It is inconſiſtent
with the Stability of the Covenant, that is well ordered in all things, and
ſure, and all its Mercies, are <hi>ſure Mercies;</hi> hence called
frequently, an Everlaſting Covenant. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32 40. <hi>And</hi> I
<hi>will I make an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Covenant with them, and I will not turn away
from them, to do them Good, but I will put my Eear in their Heart, that they
ſhall not depart from me.</hi> And all Objecting Inſtances, from
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, muſt implye no Saving Faith, or true Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or their Fall
was neither Final, nor Total. [4.] It is inconſiſtent with the
Faithfulneſs of Chriſts undertaking to God the Father in the Covenant of
Redemption, it deſtroys the Efficacy of His Death. Let any Read Chriſts
Prayer to God the Father in, <hi>John</hi> 17. And he may ſoon be
ſatisfyed, there was a Select Number given unto Chriſt to redeem and
Ranſome. 24. <hi>And Father</hi> I will <hi>that they alſo whom thou haſt
given me, be with me where,</hi> I <hi>am.</hi> And he prays, 15. <hi>And that
God would keep them from the Evil.</hi> And he has enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to God the Father,
<hi>that none that the Father bad given him, ſhould be Loſt;</hi>
otherwiſe Chriſt might be Charged with Unfaithfulneſs. And ſuch as deny
the Perſeverance of the Saints muſt be ignorant of what Chriſt has done
for the conſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Gracious State of Believers. (1) His, 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:171419:41"/>Redeeming them from all the Demands of Divine Juſtice,
with his Precious Blood. (2) Redeeming them from the power of Satan. (3) From
the Dominion of ſin. (4) He is gone to prepare a Place for them. 5 He makes
interceſſion in Heaven for them. (6) He promiſes his Holy Spirit to abide
in them, to compleat his begun work in them, and eſtabliſh them, all which
is abundantly confirmed from Scripture.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The Final and Total fall or Apoſtacy of Regenerate
Saints is inconſiſtent with the Nature of Grace which is an Incorruptible
Seed, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be totally extinguiſhed where e're it is planted of God
And farther, it much weakneth the Faith of the Saints, their Hope and
Confidence in Gods Preſervation of them from Falling which the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
and confidence of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies they firmly Believe
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35.38.39. and that in their deepeſt Tryals, and ſharpeſt
Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Finally, it Robs the Regenerated Children of God, of their
Spiritual Joy, and Holy Conſolation in the Holy-Ghoſt, by filling them with
Perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Fears Anxiety, and Doubts about their State. And we find
<hi>Keith</hi> inſinuating this, That the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Perſeverance
Flatters men in great ſins; for tho' the Godly cannot Fall, Finally nor
Totally, yet as we have ſaid, they may Fall into many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils provoking to
God, and injurious to their own Peace, and comfort, which they are ever
watchful againſt, leſt they ſhould loſe the ſenſe and comfort of
Gods Special Love, and Favour; any meaſure or degree of Grace, or Holineſs,
which would be moſt Wounding, and Grievous to them, and ſo far
<hi>from</hi> Flattery; but this his Calumny is like unto the reſt. And I
dare refer my ſelf to <hi>Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<pb n="59" facs="tcp:171419:41"/>if Univerſal Grace,
ſaving and divine Light, the Spirit of God, and Chriſt, Subſtantially
preſent in all men, even the moſt ignorant, wicked and Profane, and
abſolute Perfection in ſome, be not more ſoul-deluding, and
ſelf-Flattering Doctrine, then the Perſeverance of the Saints once
Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, whoſe ſins and infirmityes, humbled, and makes them
conſtantly watchful; and ſo it is evident, it deſtroys the promiſe of
Gods Eſtabliſhing &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Spirit, and leaves the Catholick Church
of God which the Gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt, upon a moſt
Tickliſh Foundation, and Lyable to to come to nothing; it would annul all
Chriſtian Communion and Fellowſhip, for according to <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>
opinion, one may be a Saint to day, and in Chriſtian Fellowſhip, and may
<hi>Fall away,</hi> and be Damned to morrow; it renders our Pardon
comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſeeing after Pardon we may periſh Eternally, and
deſtroyes the Hope and Faith of Life Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeing no man can
firmly believe it, until he have the Enjoyment of it.</p>
            <p>The next grand Charge, that highly offended many of that Gang, is
concerning a Queſtion in my Catechiſm concerning the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> in
the Anſwer I affirm, <hi>Quakers and</hi> Profane Perſons are Enemies to a
Sabbath, and now I am ſatisfied to have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſhowing my
reaſons to the World, how juſt, and not invidious this my Charge was,
though I mentioned no other Enemies in Judgment, beſides <hi>Quakers;</hi>
and notwithſtanding of all reaſons given to <hi>Keith</hi> and others at my
Houſe, they ſeem ſtill to be diſſatisfied, but it is for the moſt
part, the peculiar Temper of ſuch as Rangle, and oppoſe all Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
And that I may referr my ſelf to the Cenſures
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the more unprejudiced, and
rational; and I am<pb n="60" facs="tcp:171419:42"/>ſo far from Recanting, Denying, or
Giving any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for the Charge, that I am the rather confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
it was moſt juſt and deſerving, and that withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ſhadow of the guilt of a Calumny, and that fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe following reaſons. 1.
Becauſe I never met wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> any
others that in real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity oppoſed
this Doctrine be ſides that Party, and though I might hear comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Fame accuſe others, and meeting
with none of the Writings, I had no Warrant, for including them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the
publick Charge, though my Anſwer does
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> way exclude them. 2. All the
<hi>Quakers</hi> I ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with in <hi>Europe</hi> or
<hi>America,</hi> declared this a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
their undoubted Judgment, that all Dayes were alike under the Goſpel, and
none of perpetual Obſervation as a Day of Reſt; and further, That they were
as free to Work, or Labour in their ſeveral Callings and Trades on the
Firſt Day of the Week, (called now the Chriſtian Sabbath, or Day of Reſt,
under the Goſpel,) as any other Day of the Week; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which I gave, and am able yet to give ſeveral
Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: And I am lately informed, of ſeveral Servants o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quakers,</hi> otherwiſe
Educated, who have made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to Magiſtrates, of their Maſters,
cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to follow their daily
Labour; and a Witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet alive, can
declare, being on a <hi>Sabbath</hi> at <hi>Thomas Everdens</hi> Houſe,
perceived no manner of Worſhip with his Family, but great diligence in
diſpatching one of his Servants with Neceſſaries for Building a Sloop
&amp; I have met one of them with a Gun in the Wood on the Sabbath, or Firſt
Day of the Week, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> we were going
to the Publick Worſhip of God; I ſuch are not to be looked on, without any
juſt A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, of an
invidious Calumny, Enemies to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Sabbath, let the World judge. 3. They need no make ſo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at a noiſe, and clamour at this Charge 
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:171419:42"/>forhowever others may remain ignorant, yet it is not
unknown to <hi>Keith,</hi> how oft by ſeveral others <hi>Quakers</hi> have
been ranked in with ſeveral others, Enemies of the Sabbath, long before I had
any acquaintance with their principles: as by Mr <hi>John Brown,</hi> in his
Latine Treatiſe, concerning the Sabbath, alſo Mr. <hi>Matthew Crawford</hi>
in his Learned defence of the Morality of the <hi>Fourth Commandment,</hi>
called <hi>Exercitacio Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getica;</hi> therefore this charge is not mine
only, but of as many as Treat <hi>of</hi> that Subject. 4. <hi>If</hi> I
<hi>can produce their own Word, charging them with as much as I ſay, will it
not appear how unjuſtly they ſeem to to be offended at my charge;</hi> and
<hi>if</hi> any would pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe that ſmall, but angry Pamphlet <hi>of
Quakers,</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly anſwered by Mr. <hi>Mitchel of Aberdeen;</hi> and
they ſhall find it confidently aſſerted, that all Days, are alike, and
are told <hi>from Rom.</hi> 14.6. <hi>&amp; Gal.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>To
Reprehend all ſuch as obſerve one day of Seven as a Day of Reſt; and that
all Weekly Obſervation of a Day is Aboliſhed under the Goſpel;</hi> And
how <hi>Keith</hi> comes in now <hi>of</hi> Late to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell us <hi>of</hi> their keeping
the firſt <hi>Day of the Week,</hi> without being firſt reconciled to his
<hi>own Brethren,</hi> both <hi>in Practice, and Judgment;</hi> And it yet
remains <hi>for</hi> him to declare, <hi>By what Authority, or from what
Command they keep that Day, and not another; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is commanded of God,
or only an Eccleſiastick, and Humane Conſtitution, which until proved to be
the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous Judgment of</hi> Quakers, <hi>must be looked upon to be the
Private Judgment of</hi> Keith <hi>only.</hi> But he is Pleaſed to ſay,
<hi>That</hi> Quakers <hi>keep the firſt Day of the Week, and ſpend it in
the Religious Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe of
Publick, and Private Worſhip;</hi> but this is <pb n="62" facs="tcp:171419:43"/>ſaid,
and not Proved; <hi>for</hi> the contrary is know to moſt who reſort
<hi>to,</hi> and <hi>frequent</hi> their Houſe where they diſcern no more
Worſhip in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their
Families, than in the Families of <hi>Indians:</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He Appeals to their Neighbours as Witneſses,</hi>
but <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their Witneſset
have affirmed the contrary, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
they can attest to a Worſhip which can be neith ſeen nor heard, it paſses
my skill to Determine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, As many as know <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
cannot be ignorant, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
from Obedience to God or Man, could
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſwaded to obſerve the
Firſt Day <hi>of</hi> the We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
but would keep open their Shops, and follow th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeveral Callings; <hi>for</hi> which they were often dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Priſons, and their Goods carryed
away; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was not done in a Corner,
but manifeſt <hi>&amp;</hi> know to all. And tho' <hi>Keith</hi> blamed me,
<hi>for</hi> not cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Mr.
<hi>John Calume,</hi> as an Enemy, as well as they but had not the leaſt
reaſon <hi>for</hi> ſo doing, <hi>for</hi> I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>oft</hi> converſed with
<hi>Calumiſts,</hi> and Read the Writing <hi>of</hi> his Followers, who
ſtoutly defended the Moral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>of</hi> a Sabbath, or the <hi>Fourth C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmand.</hi> And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ever over zealous miſtake that Eminent Man
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God was under, when he Wrote
his <hi>Inſtituti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> yet in
his <hi>Expoſition</hi> on <hi>Genoſis,</hi> about Eight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Years after he Wrote his
<hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> owns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Morality <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Fourth Command,</hi> and it could
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ceremonial, ſeeing the
<hi>Inſtitution of</hi> a perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Sabbath,</hi> was before all Ceremonies, and that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was <hi>Calums</hi> laſt
Sentiments, is not only Evid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> from
that <hi>Commentary,</hi> but alſo <hi>from</hi> the Princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Practices, <hi>of</hi> the
<hi>Reformed Churches of Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
and <hi>Geneva, of</hi> which <hi>Callume</hi> was the Firſt <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Now all theſe things
duely conſidered, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
together, I leave it to any to determine, how
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:171419:43"/>they are
wronged in being reckoned with, or numbered among the Enemies to a Sabbath;
which has ſet their peeviſh Spirit in a flame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Catechiſm,
and ſtirred up their Venom againſt me, which I ever ſhall little
regard</p>
            <p>In page 28 I am Charged with Deficiency, concerning Miniſters,
and that in three things: and I am ready to own I have wilfully Omitted twice
three things concerning Miniſters Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Call; and pray where
is the crime. ſeeing there are ſo full Treatiſes by others on that
Subject already Publiſhed; and all I intended in my Catechiſm for Young
Ones, was only to lay down the ſeveral Duties of Miniſters and People; and
if I had been guilty of an Omiſſion in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration, he might have
found fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; but I muſt take
notice of an invidious Parentheſis, that Peoples Maintaining their
Miniſters is a main thing with me. Let the Reader examine my Catechiſm, and
he ſhall not find ground for this malicious Reflection; for it is
expreſſed in as few words as any other Duty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in ſiſting
thereon, and this was the expreſſion of an abſolute Stranger to me, and
my practice in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to a Maintainance, to which I am bold to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert,
I have been ever undenied as <hi>Keith,</hi> or any of his Brethren. And
whatever others have done, I dare affirm, I never bargained with any people
about a Maintainance; and have oft refuſed mony when free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered, and
never Enjoyed any Maintainance, but what was moſt freely offered to me;
though I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eny not to the
Magiſtrate, a power of Determining Maintainances, when Neceſſity requires
it; and none ſo unwilling to pay it as perverſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> though I
could wiſh it were voluntary Offerings; yet this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Author would
inſinuate, as if Presbyterians only <pb n="64" facs="tcp:171419:44"/>were Guilty; exacting
Maintainance by force; whereas he cannot be ignorant, that the Maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of
Miniſters in <hi>Scotland,</hi> are not to be compared to what Prelates have,
whether Popiſh or Proteſtant, neither for quantity, nor manner of Exacting.
And it is obſervable, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> have been brawling and
barking unreaſonably againſt all who receive Maintainance, as Hirelings;
but the greateſt Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions among them, were never able to defend ſo bad a
Cauſe, as they have been tenacious in for a long time; though now of late,
they ſeem to change their Tunes, and own a Maintainance, providing it be
voluntary, and not by Compulſion, as <hi>Barclay</hi> has owned, who has
taken upon him to Publiſh <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles, though he never
produced any Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it; and I am perſwaded, he will find it as
hard a matter to procure their univerſal Conſent, and Approbation to all he
has Wrote; but a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Maintainance among <hi>Quakers</hi> muſt be
volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and free, for they would never Exact it by force, for two
Reaſons. 1. Becauſe they never had the Government ſolely in their Hands,
for in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> they are a mixed people; neither would the
Infancy of that Plantation bear it; beſide that, their forme Railings would
have Retorted upon themſelves. 2 Becauſe of the multitude of their
Teachers, and the Weakneſs of many of them, that dare not claim a Right to
any ſuch Maintainance, as many ſilly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ignorant Mechanicks. And
it muſt be for meaſure or quantity, a neceſſary Competency, or
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment, as <hi>Barclay</hi> calls it; but muſt <hi>Quakers</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> be Judges of this Competency, or
ſhould the Give, or rather the Civil Magiſtrate to determine it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the ſeveral Abilities of the People: And conſider what narrow and
niggardly Souls theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<pb n="65" facs="tcp:171419:44"/>have, who would allow no
more to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, then common Charity obliges them to
give to the moſt common beggar that goes from Door to Door, even a
neceſſary Competency, and Aliment; whereas Miniſters ſhould have ſuch
a Maintainance as they may not be neceſſitated to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle, and incumber
themſelves with ſecular Affairs, and be diverted from their holy Office,
and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Calling, whereunto they have been Called, and to which they
are to be Separated according to the Command of God, concerning <hi>Paul</hi>
and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas;</hi> and further, they ought to have ſuch an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Allowance, as they may not only Live an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their Station, and be
able to maintain Duties to Hoſpitality, which <hi>Quakers</hi> Competency,
and neceſſary Aliment, will never render them capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perform: And it
were no hard matter to prove, that many <hi>Quakers,</hi> even <hi>Keith</hi>
and <hi>Barclay</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whoſe Birth, Education, Travels and
Eſtates are known to many yet alive, have had much more given then their
neceſſary Aliment.</p>
            <p>And I know not what Evaſion can be found for <hi>K</hi>'s
Hundred Pound <hi>Per Annum</hi> ſetled on him by the <hi>Government in
Penſilvania,</hi> Exacted <hi>of</hi> a mixed People, who neither hear him,
nor enjoy any benefit or advantage from his School-Keeping, which is their only
ſhift and Back-Door, they would fly out at; which will never Blind the eyes
<hi>of</hi> the Rational; <hi>for</hi> School-Keeping has a peculiar advantage
attending it ſelf, without any Publick Tax by compulſion, as they call all
our Mentai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. And I Dare be bold to ſay, in behalf <hi>of
Presbyterians</hi> whom he would chiefly ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, that they are as
little concerned about men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainances as any of the Reformed Churches, and 
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:171419:45"/>value them not, when they come in competition with theirs
And have not the Miniſters of the Reformed Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
theſe Thirty years paſt, have ſuffered Perſecution, even unto Death
i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, for preaching the
Goſpel under ſo much want, that they have been neceſſitated to Labour
with their own hands, and betake themſelves for a time to Merchandiſing,
and yet never would dare to lay aſide the Preaching of the Goſpel. And it
is not unknown, how little Miniſters have had <hi>of</hi> Mentainance in
<hi>Maryland,</hi> either voluntary or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled; And <hi>Quakers</hi>
themſelves, own they have Stock Purſes, out of which they Supply their
Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and others; and what call you this but a Maintainance; and it is
moſt eaſy when they come abroad, to conceal their Plenty at home, that the
Stock Purſes may be the more Liberal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as I doubt not but thoſe
of <hi>Maryland, &amp; Virginia</hi> too, were in his Late Travels, which was
the leaſt he could have, for he gained but few <hi>Proſelytes.</hi> And let
all Judge how inconſiſtent their preſent practices are, with their former
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable pratling againſt every thing that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like a Maintenance,
urging as <hi>K.</hi> ſtill does that Text, <hi>Freely ye have Received,
Freely Give,</hi> which was the Advice of Our Saviour to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, when
he enabled them to go forth and work Miracles, <hi>Heal the Sick, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſe the Leper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Raiſe the Dead, Caſt out Devi's,</hi> of which they ſhould
make no Merchandize; tho' they were <hi>Commanded to Preach the Goſpel as
they go along, telling them that the Time of the Promiſed</hi> Meſſiah,
<hi>was now come, who was ſetting up his Kingdom in the World, and to whoſe
Laws ther were to be obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
This Doctrine they were to confirm by Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,<pb n="67" facs="tcp:171419:45"/>which he gives them a Charge, they
ſhould work freely, <hi>without receiving any Reward for them;</hi> that the
Miracles being uſed to their private uſe, and profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, might not loſe their End, which was the confirmation
of their Doctrine; now it hereby was underſtood they ſhould reci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve no neceſſary Maintenance, the
Apoſtles might Rationally Judge, they had need then to provide well for their
jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; no, as, <hi>if</hi> Our Lord had ſaid, <hi>Provide nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gold,
nor Silv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, nor Braſs in your
Purſes, nor Scrip for your Journer, neither two Coats, neither ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, nor ſtaves;</hi> and the reaſon added, for the
workman is worthy of his Meat, and elſe where, is worthy of his Hire, and
pray what is Meat, and Hire, but the beſt of Maintenance; and it is
obſervable, the Command for going abroad ſo bare, in the 10 of
<hi>Matthew</hi> was only a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Command for that ſhort Journey; for in
Luke; they were commanded to take both <hi>Purſe</hi> and <hi>Scrip,</hi> ch
22 If they were commanded to take none of theſe things and yet to go abroad,
and Preach the Goſpel, confirming the ſame with Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, they muſt have
received maintenance, or they muſt have periſhed if their Journey had been
long; but Our Lord deſigned thereby (1) To give his Apoſtles an experience
of depending on his Good Providence and (2) Alſo teach people, That the
Labourer is worthy of his Hire; and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Keith</hi> conſider that in reſpect of God all things is
free, therefore his School-keeping ſhould be free alſo. And it is not to be
doubted, that our Saviour took Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance himſelf, ſometimes asking,
ſometimes taking without asking, what he ſtood in need of, as Water from
the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman, and the Ears of Corn on the Sabbath. And it is to
be admited with what<pb n="68" facs="tcp:171419:46"/>Impudence Quakers plead againſt the
Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in denying the lawfulneſs of Miniſterial Receiving
a Maintainance, ſeeing he gives ſo particular a Precept, Gal. 6.6. <hi>Let
him that is Taught in the Word, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate unto him that Teacheth, in all
good things;</hi> and if this be the Command of God, it muſt be Sin in the
people to omit it. But the ſame Apoſtle pleads for, and reaſons the
caſe fully, 1 Cor. 9. wherein he has many convincing Arguments againſt all
<hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in the world; proving firſt, That the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of
Miniſters and Families is warrantable, from 4, 5, 6 verſes. 2. In the
following Verſe he declares the Law ſays as much, both the Law of God and
the Law of Nature, built upon Equity, pleads for it, 8, 9, 10 <hi>verſe.</hi>
3. Common Equity and Juſtice pleads for it, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. <hi>If we
have ſown to you Spiritual Things, is it a great thing, if we ſhall Reap
your Carnal Things;</hi> yet all <hi>Pauls</hi> forbearing at ſeveral times
to partake of Peoples Carnal Things, did not at all demonſtrate the
unlawfulneſs thereof, but only his prudential declining of that he had really
a Right unto as expreſſed, <hi>verſe</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>If others be Partakers of this power over you, are not we rather:
Nevertheleſs we have not uſed this power, but ſuffer all things, leſt
we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt, and this was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he
wrought, with his own Hands; and Laſtly the Apoſtle concludes with the
Neceſſity of Miniſters living by the Goſpel, they Preach from the
Ordination of God 14. Even ſo hath the Lord Ordained, that they that Preach
the Goſpel, ſhould Live of the Goſpel. But if <hi>Quakers</hi> all this
while, are only againſt Superfluous Maintenances they have loſt their
Labour, for we pleaded not for ſuch, not for any other accidental Abuſes,
that through<pb n="69" facs="tcp:171419:46"/>Corruption of time, hath been introduced; but
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that know their Quibbling, and Tenacious Temper, are ſatisfied they will
never yield the Cauſe, until they are the ſole Judges of that
Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity.</p>
            <p>Another thing in this Charge, which needs an Anſwer: And that is
concerning the Call and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Miniſters, which I did not intend to
Treat of at all in my <hi>Catechiſm</hi> Publiſhed for the inſtruction of
<hi>Young Ones,</hi> and if this Point be one of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Firſt
Principles they ſhould be more diſtinct and clear in proving the Call, and
Ordination of their <hi>Maſculine and Feminine Teachers,</hi> which they are
Pleaſed to Call <hi>Immediate, Extraordinary,</hi> and <hi>Apostolick,</hi>
of which <hi>K</hi> in a vain manner Publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Privately, has Boaſted
and Affirmed the ſame, at my Houſe: And in his Paper charges all others,
<hi>That they Run to the Church or Pope of Rome,</hi> for their <hi>Call</hi>
and <hi>Miſſion,</hi> and this he would ſeem (to the Ignorant) to
Reaſon ſo Profoundly, as if it would confound all gainſayers, but,</p>
            <p>I ſhall Firſt Examine <hi>Quakers Immediate Miſſion,</hi>
the Call ſo much talked of, but never yet proved, by any demonſtration, but
their own words, which ſhall never be wanting to <hi>Falſe Teachers,</hi>
who <hi>go about to Decieve;</hi> and I am perſwaded <hi>Quakers,</hi> muſt
have no ſmall conceit of themſelves, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their bare words, ſhould
have more Credit with Men, then Chriſt, or his Apoſtles expected theirs
ſhould have received in the World in their Day; for they brought in no ſuch
ſlender, but more Convincing Teſtimonies, able to perſwade all, as
<hi>Nicodemus</hi> confeſſeth of Chriſt, <hi>No man can do the works that
thou doeſt or Miracles, except God be with him.</hi> And this we Believe, and
that with<pb n="70" facs="tcp:171419:47"/>Warrant from the <hi>Word of God,</hi> that we are
to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no <hi>Immediate or Extraordinary Miſſion,</hi> or
<hi>can,</hi> even from the <hi>Higheſt Pretenders</hi> without
<hi>Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> and <hi>Anſwerable</hi> Demonſtrations; as Our
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> when <hi>John</hi> ſent His Diſciples to be informed,
<hi>Whether he was the Promiſed Meſſiah?</hi> and our <hi>Lord,</hi> who
might have eaſily diſpatched them with words, bids them, <hi>Go</hi> and
tell him, <hi>The Lame Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, the
Sick are healed, and the Blind receive their ſight; and Let him, not truſt
Words, Leſt Seducers, ſhould take an Opportunity, and Advantage thereby to
deceive.</hi> And when <hi>Quakers</hi> are purſued hotly about
<hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> they Smilingly ſay, <hi>John the Baptiſt wrought
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Miracles, and yet his
Miſſion was Extraordinary, and immediate,</hi> as <hi>K.</hi> Alledged at
my Houſe,; and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> improved it,
and Particularly againſt the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> England Miniſters;</hi> and they <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> they have
gained the <hi>Day;</hi> but methinks, <hi>K.</hi> as <hi>I told him,</hi> and
<hi>all others</hi> may juſtly be aſhamed of Producing this all an
inſtance for the Future; <hi>for,</hi> tho' <hi>John wrought no Miracles, yet
being Co-temporary with our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and his Apostles, and they who
wrought many Miracles, confirmed this Miſſion, that he was the Promiſed
Elias;</hi> but the <hi>Immediate Miſſion of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> never was
confirmed, either by their own, of by the <hi>Miracles</hi> of others; tho'
ſome of them have preſumed boldly on <hi>Miracles,</hi> which Propheſeing
Miracles, As the <hi>Eating Quaker</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (Juſtly made the
<hi>Monument</hi> of Gods <hi>Wrath,</hi> and <hi>Monſter</hi> of
<hi>Mankind</hi>) For daring to <hi>imitate</hi> Our <hi>Lord</hi> in that
<hi>Miraculous Action of His Faſting, Forty Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and Forty Nights in the Wilderneſs.</hi> And
<hi>Solomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ackles</hi> who
<hi>Boaſtingly challenged Miniſters to Faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with him, and Juſtly Puniſhed for his
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hold
Arrogance.</hi> Another once in <hi>Barbadoes, to<pb n="71" facs="tcp:171419:47"/>king upon
him, to Prophecy the Death of a Child, which in all humane Probability was
beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Recovery; but GOD to confound his</hi> Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<hi>and diſcover him to be a Deceiver, was pleaſed to restore the
Child,</hi> who <hi>Lived in health for many Jews, and the Quaking Prophet was
neceſſitated ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to Publiſh his Recantation, wherein he
affirmed, he had Belyed the Spirit of God.</hi> And if ſo, it is no
<hi>Wonder</hi> they <hi>Belye</hi> their <hi>Neighbours;</hi> but any
<hi>man</hi> may <hi>ſee</hi> how they <hi>come off</hi> with their <hi>Lying
Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and ſo ſhall <hi>come off</hi> in the <hi>End,</hi> with
their <hi>immediate Miſſion:</hi> but it is at Length, come to this, that
you muſt recieve their <hi>Verbal testimony,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main altogether
diſſatisfyed, about their <hi>Extraordinary Call,</hi> tho' ſome as
<hi>Keith</hi> informed us, at <hi>my houſe</hi> run that Self-Confounding,
and Univerſal Gulf of Miracles in <hi>Spirit,</hi> a <hi>New invented
Phraſe, of worſe then mans Wiſdome,</hi> far from the <hi>Language</hi>
of the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> whoſe Saving <hi>Operations</hi> are not
<hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> at all, to the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and if
<hi>Miracles,</hi> they are Gods Properly, and not <hi>Quakers,</hi> but this
with many more Phraſes of heirs, has no <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the
Scriptures</hi> And we deſire to <hi>know</hi> how many <hi>of</hi> them ever
<hi>Spake</hi> with <hi>Tongues,</hi> who were not <hi>Taught</hi> them in the
<hi>School,</hi> or Learned them of <hi>others.</hi> Farewel then <hi>immediate
Miſſion,</hi> if you take it not upon the Words of a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independants,</hi> and
then only, as he invidiouſly expreſſes it, ſhould run to the <hi>Church
of Rome</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> for to derive the <hi>miſſion,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> and <hi>ordinition</hi>
from thence; is the groſſeſt <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ny,</hi> and moſt notorious <hi>Lye,</hi> that could be
<hi>batched</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of
<hi>hell;</hi> and muſt be of <hi>Satan</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of
<hi>Lyes:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut if <hi>K</hi>
had aſſerted this, of ſuch has hold no <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but from the
hands of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Prelate,</hi> he<pb n="72" facs="tcp:171419:48"/>might
have had ſome plea for his charge; for <hi>Rome,</hi> and all that Party
ſufficiently know, there are none ſo oppoſite to, nor ſo
<hi>faithful,</hi> and <hi>Zealous</hi> againſt them as Diſſenting
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> were; no not <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves, who would
not have been ſo great at the <hi>Engliſh Court,</hi> in the late Reign, if
they had; therefore a <hi>Noted Perſon</hi> lately gained from <hi>Rome,</hi>
affirmed, <hi>The Diſsenting Protestants, were the Bulwarks of the Protestant
Intereſt in Europe.</hi> And I muſt greatly ſuſpect, what <hi>K</hi>
told me, at my Houſe, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lye,</hi> and <hi>Calumny,</hi> that
Mr. <hi>John Cotton,</hi> of <hi>Hampton,</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi>
acknowledged in a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Diſpute, that <hi>He derived his Ordination from
the Pope,</hi> and the rather, becauſe he abuſed me, upon his Return, to
Mr. <hi>Davis,</hi> affirming the ſame thing of me; that, <hi>I owned cur
Miſſion, and Ordination, from the Pope of Rome;</hi> but I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident,
his own Conſcience could not but witneſs the contrary to his Face [But it
is to be Feared, it was not the Firſt time, he had Learned to Baffle
Conſcience in more Weighty Matters] For I not only Abhorred, Diſclaimed,
and Denyed it; but Poſitively, and Plainly, Affirmed, <hi>Our Miſſion was
from Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Warranted from the Scriptures.</hi> Hence I
give caution to all, not to be Credulous of <hi>K</hi>'s words, however ſo
confidently affirmed; but he were no fit <hi>Deciever,</hi> if nor
<hi>Poſseſsed</hi> with a <hi>Spirit of Lyes, and Calumnys</hi> But we can
eaſily Juſtify ourſelves from this Aſperſion thrown invidiouſly
upon us by <hi>Quakers,</hi> and particularly, by <hi>K.</hi> in all his
Publick, and Private Diſcourſes, and alſo in ſome of his Writings,
repeated over and over, with an empty noiſe of Words for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we ſhould ſay with
<hi>Calvin,</hi> that he and others o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Primitive Reformers were <hi>Evangiliſts,</hi>
extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily<pb n="73" facs="tcp:171419:48"/>Raiſed, and Immediately Called of God, in
that great Exigence of the Church, in calling the People of God out of Popiſh
Darkneſs, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, in bringing them out of Babylon; yet this will
prove but a ſlender Argument for <hi>Quakers</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Extraordinary
Calls, and immediate Miſſions, to be Gods ordinary and uſual
uninterrupted way to the end of the World; becauſe it might be allowed of in
that juncture of the Neceſſity of the Church; for though our Lord
himſelf, the King of his Church, at the beginning of the Promulgation of the
Goſpel, Called ſome in an Extraordinary Manner; though at the ſame time,
they had an External Call from Chriſt as man; yet as ſoon as the
Chriſtian Church began to Encreaſe, he Commands them to uſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Means for that Calling, and Separation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Holy Office of the
Miniſtry in an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and Holy Separation to that Sacred Work, as
<hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was commanded to be Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and there
was Caſting of Lots uſed in ſupplying the number of the Apoſtles; and
the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Timothy,</hi> and Impowers him to
Ordain Elders in every Church, and not to neglect the Gift that was given him
by Prophecy, with the Laying on of the Hands of <hi>the Presbytery,</hi> who
are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to Lay Hands ſuddenly on no man without ſufficient proof of
his Parts, and Piety. And further, for their direction in this Scriptural and
Orderly Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and Ordination, God has laid down all the Qualifications of
Miniſters of the Goſpel; which <hi>Quakers</hi> can never find in all their
Teachers, eſpecially of the Feminine Sex.</p>
            <p>As to our Reformers receiving their Ordination, Miſſion and
Call from <hi>Rome,</hi> and conveying it to us, which would ſeem to be the
firſt great puzling and<pb n="74" facs="tcp:171419:49"/>confounding Argument. I ſhall
anſwer it in theſe following particulars. 1. I would inquire of all
<hi>Quakers,</hi> whether God in that great defection and univerſal
Corruption of the Church, under <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolatry, had then a Church
in the World, though in the Wilderneſs; to deny all Churches, whether
Viſible or Inviſible, really belonging to God, &amp; Jeſus Chriſt, were
to overthrow many Promiſes of God to his Church, of Building her upon an
immoveable Rock and that the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail againſt her,
and it is inconſiſtent to ſay, God had a Church among the <hi>Jews</hi>
under their Defections, and Failings away to Idolatry, and Superſtition: Now
where Chriſt has a Church, though Inviſible &amp; in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,
there are the Eſſentials of Religion, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and
Church-conſtitution, tho' much infected with Error, and corrupted with
Romiſh Superſtition, and theſe Eſſentials are ſtill Gods, and to
eſteem his and not theirs, who are the chief Inſtruments, Heads, and
Authors of all the Corruptions, under that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to whom only and properly
belong thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Corruptions, Idolatries and Superſtitions they have
invented and introduced to the Church; And yet the ſoundeſt of Divines
believe, that upon all Reformations, which undoubtedly are originally and
efficiently of God; a people, or particular perſons leaving and Renouncing
the Abominations of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and their ſubmitting to, and embracing the
Truth of the Goſpel, and the Purity of all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Worſhip,
abandoning the <hi>Pope</hi> as their Head, and Subjecting themſelves to
Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they are <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> Conſtituted Churches of
Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and the Goſpel Truths, Ordination and Ordinances, VVord
and Sacraments they adhere to, are not theirs, nor from thoſe they Separated
from,<pb n="75" facs="tcp:171419:49"/>is <hi>Keith</hi> ignorantly and invidiouſly
aſſerts; but they are ſtill the Lords, and belong to Jeſus Chriſt;
for even in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and under Antichriſt, there were
Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, VVord and Sacraments, Praying Preaching, and
Praiſing of God; tho' much vailed and corrupted; and conſequently they had
Miniſters or Officers to Diſpenſe theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, who undoubtedly
had ſome of the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Ordination, which was the Lords, and
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was properly Antichriſts, but Antichriſtian Corruptions, of which
he is Author; for <hi>differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia constituit ſpeciem:</hi> ſo that we no
more have Ordination from the Pope, upon Reformation, then we have Baptiſm,
and the Lords Supper, Reading and Praiſing; and <hi>Quakers</hi> have Prayer,
Teaching the Scriptures, and their new Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Firſt Day of the
VVeek.</p>
            <p>And we would gladly know from what part of Gods Word is it, or can
it be made to appear, that upon every Defection and Corruption of the Church;
God will Beget and Create New Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in an immediate manner under the
Goſpel, more man under the Law; For after the Defections <hi>of
Iſrael,</hi> and long continuance in Idolatry, upon their Repentance and
Reformation from all their Corup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Abuſes, they were Re
Eſtabliſhed &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>itred unto all the Ordinances, and
Priviledges of the Church of God; and what does <hi>Keith</hi> think of them,
and their Reformation, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are he
affirm they had all their Ordination and VVorſhip from <hi>Jereboam, Who
made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to Sin,</hi> and other chief Idolaters; ſo it will
unqueſtionably follow, that neither we, our Ordination, Doctrine, VVorſhip,
nor Sacraments, while warranted from the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly of Gods VVord, are from <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope, 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:171419:50"/>or any Prelate in the VVorld, as <hi>Quakers,</hi> after
the manner of Satan, would Accuſe the <hi>Brethren.</hi> Thus <hi>Keiths</hi>
invincible <hi>Armado</hi> is beat to pieces; whereby he thought to have
overthrown all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who have obeyed Gods Call; and are come out of
Babylon. And we are confident that a great part of our Teachings are
Chriſtian Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to which we oft publickly do Appeal for Confirmation
of what is delivered, and many Preachers have a peculiar way of Preaching their
own Experiences.</p>
            <p>And finally, as he begins, ſo he cloſes &amp; ſhuts up his
Paper with groundleſs, &amp; Falſe Calumnies, and invidious Reflections;
affirming, I aſſert and alledge Falſe things, concerning
<hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and Firſt concerning
<hi>Baptiſm,</hi> (he ſaith) Firſt, I do not diſtinguiſh between
<hi>Johns Baptiſm,</hi> and Chriſts; In anſwer to this, I Freely
aſſent to any, and all the diſtinction made in the Scriptures; which is
not in Subſtance, or Eſſence, but in Fruit, and Efficacy, and the ſame
diſtinction I ſtill make between our External Adminiſtration, and
Chriſts Efficacious Bleſſing thereof: for what <hi>John</hi> ſaid, we
and all Miniſters of the Goſpel to the end of the World, muſt ſtill
acknowledge; we <hi>Baptiſe</hi> with <hi>Water,</hi> but Chriſt, and he
alone, <hi>Baptiſeth</hi> with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and with
<hi>Fire,</hi> And if the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> Adminiſtred by Chriſts
Diſciples, in His <hi>Name,</hi> Authority and Preſence, was Chriſts and
no doubt it was the ſame with <hi>Johns</hi> for Subſtance, as you or any
other may Read <hi>John</hi> 2.22, 23, 24, 26. <hi>verſes.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> wherewith Chriſt and His
Diſciples Baptiſed in the Land <hi>of Judea</hi> was <hi>Water
Baptiſm.</hi> 2. It was an outward, viſible, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable 
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:171419:50"/>Baptiſm to Spectators; ſaith <hi>Johns</hi>
Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to him, <hi>Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond</hi> Jordan,
<hi>the ſame Baptizeth, and</hi> all <hi>men come unto him:</hi> it is
obſervable, that it was not the Baptiſm with the Holy Ghoſt and with
Fire, as diſtinct from the outward Ordinance; <hi>for</hi> it is ſaid,
<hi>John</hi> 4.2. <hi>Jeſus himſelf Baptiſed not, but His
Diſciples;</hi> yet it is called his, in the 1 <hi>v. of</hi> this
<hi>chap.</hi> and in the 22. <hi>v. of</hi> the <hi>former chap</hi> (1)
Becauſe done by his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. (2) By his Command, and Authority. And it
was the ſame <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> his Diſciples, and Apoſtles, performed
in all and Every Church, where they Preached the Goſpel, according to that
laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion <hi>of</hi> Our Lords, immediately before His
Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, <hi>Matth</hi> 28. and laſt <hi>Go Teach, and Baptiſe al
Nations, and Lo</hi> I <hi>am with you, to the end of the World.</hi> Hence
Four things are obſervable in this Text. 1 That, <hi>Teaching of
Nations,</hi> yea, <hi>All Nations,</hi> by external means, and inſtruments,
is a Standing and Perpetual Ordinance in the Church <hi>of</hi> Chriſt, to
the end <hi>of</hi> the World. 2 That, as many as are Called Miniſters of the
Goſpel, are alſo Commiſſionated <hi>To Baptiſe alſo, Go Teach all
Nations Baptiſing them.</hi> 3 That <hi>Water Baptiſm,</hi> or the External
Ordinance, is that Enjoined, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Words, and not the
<hi>Baptiſm</hi> with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and with <hi>Fire; for</hi>
it is enjoined to meer men who can do no more then <hi>John</hi> could do, who
Profeſſed he <hi>Baptiſed</hi> with <hi>Water,</hi> and yet we believe
many who were <hi>Baptiſed</hi> by <hi>John,</hi> received alſo the
<hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> otherwiſe a very empty, and inſignificant Ordinance,
and unprofitable to all, if nothing elſe was reaped thereby, but
<hi>Sprinkling,</hi> or <hi>Waſhing with Water;</hi> and yet the Outward
Mean, Ordinance, and Adminiſtration, was from <hi>John,</hi> 
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:171419:51"/>and the fruit, efficacy and bleſſing, was from
<hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and it is bold impudence, and Arrogant Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,
for any to pretend to Baptiſe with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt and with Fire, which is
Chriſts peculiar Work, and Prerogative. And <hi>Keiths</hi> anſwer here
unto in his Book, is void of all ſatisfaction to any Intelligent Perſon;
for he affirms, tho' no man Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize with the Holy Ghoſt efficiently, yet
they may inſtrumentally; we who uſe the outward mean, Inſtrument and
Ordinance, may through the Bleſſing of God, and Efficacious Preſence of
Chriſt's Spirit, and undoubtedly are made Inſtruments of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grace,
Life, and Advantage of that Ordinance: but how <hi>Quakers</hi> can be
Inſtruments of Baptizing Spiritually, who are oppoſite to, and ridicule the
outward Ordinance, which is the only proper means and inſtrument of Gods own
Appointment, I cannot reſolve; unleſs they will take Gods place, by
work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Means, and contrary to Means; or they imagine to work Effects
by unſuitable cauſes, and attain an end by improper means; as if a man
inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Merchandize, by Labouring in the Ground, intend for
<hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>America,</hi> and yet Steer to the <hi>South;</hi> or
by Planting Tobacco, to imagine to Reap Corn; for I am perſwaded, that ſuch
as in Faith Adminiſters the outward Ordinance of Baptiſm, and that purely
according to the Divine Inſtitution, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Depending on God for his
Bleſſing, and Chriſt for his Vertue, and Preſence, are in the moſt
probable way of being Inſtruments of the Grace of Baptiſm; ſo that this
Baptiſm is a ſtanding and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Ordinance, to the End of the World;
which is clearly inferred from the Promiſe annexed, which is perpetual; and,
<hi>Lo I am with you to the End of the World,</hi> as durable as Teaching it
ſelf, which the after<pb n="79" facs="tcp:171419:51"/>practice <hi>of the Apostles,</hi>
and Servants of Chriſt to this day Confirm, &amp; ſhould be continued until
Chriſt's Second Coming, notwithſtanding of all Gainſayers. He further
would inſinuate, That we Learned and Received Sprinkling of Children <hi>from
the Church of</hi> Rome; but it is eaſy to make appear, they go hand in hand
with <hi>Rome</hi> in more things than we do, who are known to all the
Followers of Antichriſt to walk more oppoſite to; and in abhorrence of
their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practices, then any others: for their Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
Redemption, their Free-will, their denying Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, their
<hi>poſſible Perfection in this Life, their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipending the
Scriptures,</hi> and denying it to be the Rule, and their holding <hi>the Pope
of Rome</hi> not to be <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> and <hi>their Denying the
Morality of the Fourth Command,</hi> they have raked and picked theſe with
many more out of that filthy Sink, and ſtinking pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Romiſh
Corruption; and as for our Sprinkling in Baptiſm, it is not ſo repugnant to
Scripture, as perverſe <hi>Quakers</hi> do imagine: For Water in Baptiſm,
Repreſents the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and why not <hi>ſprinkling, the
Sprinkling of the Blood of Christ,</hi> which is ſo clearly expreſſed by
the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> but neither <hi>Infant
Baptiſm, nor Sprinkling</hi> is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Controverſy between
<hi>Quakers</hi> and us; for 1 They are againſt the <hi>Baptiſm of Old as
well as Young.</hi> (2.) They are againſt <hi>Waſhing or Dipping as well as
Sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing;</hi> therefore I wave
both. And next, I ſhall make appear, That <hi>George Keith is guilty of a
double falſhood</hi> concerning <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in his Book. 1. In
oppoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scripture, to
ſay with his Brethren, that Water
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aptiſm was only for
<hi>Johns</hi> Diſpenſation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ently Aboliſhed, or abrogated in Chriſt; whereas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was continued all the time of
Chriſt's Life, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he was
Dead and Gone, and ſtill does without<pb n="80" facs="tcp:171419:52"/>all interruption, as
any may read in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtle 2 He contradicteth
himſelf, and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren too, in ſaying, <hi>that only it ſtood in
force in</hi> Johns <hi>time, and aboliſhed immediately;</hi> yet ſome may
be Sent of the Lord, and Inſtructed to Baptiſe with Water, and if they can
prove they are Sent of the Lord, ſhould be gladly Received; but <hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Labor, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Opus eſt;</hi> for how they go about to prove this,
they have never yet told us. Now let his Friends and Followers conſider and
examine, what this man would be at; for it is aboliſhed, and yet they may be
called by the Spirit of God to Adminiſter it; can it be ſuppoſed, that
the Spirit of God will call any to Adminiſter that Worſhip, that is Removed
and Aboliſhed by God and His Holy Spirit; were not this to make God and His
Holy Spirit, who are Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially one, to Claſh with themſelves, which
were Blaſphemy to affirm? He impugnes <hi>Water Baptiſm,</hi> with all his
might, as not now warranted by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and yet will Juſtifie a Call, and
Miſſion to Adminiſter Abrogated Worſhip; and from the ſame Argument,
why not Called and Sent to perform all the Abrogated Services, Rites and
Sacrifices under the Law, as <hi>Circumciſion, the Paſsover, and all Legal
Sacrifices;</hi> and ſo from a pretended Call, to ſet up again the
<hi>Moſaical Worſhip?</hi> This would be a brave Spiritual Work indeed; and
to make this appear to be the Judgment of others of that Party, as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his own; he acknowledged at my
Houſe, <hi>A Quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once
Baptiſed with Water, and was approved of for it.</hi> Is Water Baptiſm not
warranted by Scripture, but Aboliſhed ſince <hi>Johns</hi> Dayes, and yet
performed and approved of by thoſe who are Enemies thereunto, from an
imaginary, and unknown Call, and Miſſion, which would be to introduce the
groſſeſt Enthuſiaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:171419:52"/>in the World, and an open door to all wild fancies, and
imaginations? Let <hi>Keiths</hi> Friends and Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, beware of this mans
principles, and Books</p>
            <p>And concerning the Lords Supper, he aſperſes us all; but I
doubt not to make it convincingly appear, that he both contradicteth Scripture,
and his Brethren too: 1 He contradicteth Scripture, in undervaluing this great
Ordinance, as no Special, Divine, Spiritual &amp; Goſpel Ordinance; but
Jumbles it in with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and dayly Eating, and ordinary means of
Believers: an high indignity to this Ordinance, and the Author of it, repugnant
to Scripture, and inconſiſtent with the ſure, and certain experience of
thouſands <hi>of</hi> the Godly, who have <hi>Eat</hi> at the Table of the
Lord, to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable comfort, and tranſporting Conſolation, more
then they reaped by their ordinary Meals; ſo that Chriſtian Experience
witneſſeth againſt them, and confutes all their Quibling Arguments, and
Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Quirks; and my own experience of the Grace, Bleſſings, and
Benefits, of this Great Special, and Solemn Ordinance, ſhall be an
unanſwerable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to me, againſt all <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the World.
And it is alſo ſtrange, with what impudent Spirit, they can call the
<hi>Supper of the Lord</hi> no <hi>Special Ordinance</hi> diſtinct from
Ordinary Meals. For, (1) Our Lord oft Eat with Mixed Multitudes; but in this
Ordinance with a Select Number of his own, even his Apoſtles: (2) He never
did Celebrate that Ordinance, but once, and that was in the very Night,
<hi>wherein he was Betrayed:</hi> a great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Love, and
Faithfulneſs to his Church. (3) He Inſtituted it immediately after the
<hi>Paſsover,</hi> and that <hi>Hymn</hi> that was uſually <hi>Sung,</hi>
after the <hi>Paſsover,</hi> was deferred till after the Adminiſtration of
the Lords Supper, to ſignify the Abrogation of the<pb n="82" facs="tcp:171419:53"/>one,
and Inſtitution of the other in its Room, and Place. (4) At what other Meals,
did ever Our Lord ſay, <hi>This is my Body and as oft as you do it, do it in
Remembrance of me?</hi> (5) Thoſe that make their Ordinary Meals to be the
Lords Supper, which is a new notion of <hi>K</hi>'s, they alter the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements
at your Pleaſure, which are Signs inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, the <hi>Bread</hi> to
ſignify his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to ſignify his
<hi>Blood;</hi> and they Arrogantly <hi>&amp;</hi> Preſumptuouſly appoint
others, <hi>Fiſh, Fleſh,</hi> and what ever comes in the way, far from the
practice <hi>of</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Church of
<hi>Corinth,</hi> who delivered nothing to that Church in this great
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, but what he received of the Lord Jeſus, the Author of it
retaining all, the Eſſentials both <hi>for</hi> matter, and manner, waving
only ſome occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and accidental Circumſtances, therefore
Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſters it in Bread and Wine. 2 He Reflects on us, by charging us with
<hi>Popiſh Conſecrations,</hi> but in this, and many things elſe, he
cannot be ſo Ignorant, as Malicious; for he knows, we abhor all <hi>Popiſh
Conſecration;</hi> And all we do, is only to Pray to God for a Bleſſing
on the Elements, that God would be pleaſed to vouchſafe his Gracious
Preſence, and Sanctify the Elements of Bread and Wine, making his own
Ordinance Effectual, for the Spiritual Nouriſhment of Believers: and as we
Eat Bread, and Drink Wine, ſo we may Feed by Faith, and Spiritually upon
Jeſus Chriſt, and what <hi>Popery</hi> is here, let the World judge. All
this <hi>K</hi> has ſeen in our Directory for Publick Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, In his Book, he Quarrels our Eating in this Ordinance
ſo Sparingly, and would ſeem to approve of a Plentiful Meal, and a full
Stomach, and commend the Quantity; but I am ſure this is<pb n="83" facs="tcp:171419:53"/>not Spiritual, but Carnal: Arguing to the Pamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Fleſh;
and Flatly contrary to the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion <hi>Paul</hi> gives to the carnal
<hi>Corinthians,</hi> even Eating at the Lords Table, to the Nouriſhment of
their Bodies; which was a great and Sinful abuſe of that Holy Ordinance, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. <hi>What have ye not Houſes to Eat and Drink in, or
deſpiſe ye the Church of God;</hi> ſhowing that Eating the Lords Supper,
is another thing then Eating at home, only to the Nouriſhment of our Bodys,
for which the Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lords Supper was never inſtituted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Brief Narrative of a Late Difference among <hi>Quakers</hi>
begun at <hi>Philadelphia.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving in <hi>August</hi> 1692. Satisfied my Longing Deſire, in
viſiting <hi>Penſilvania, I</hi> no ſooner Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived in that Government,
but perceived a Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Difference between the Geſtures, <hi>&amp;</hi>
Behaviour of <hi>Quakers</hi> there, <hi>&amp;</hi> all others I have been
acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with elſewhere, Males, and Females; uſing that Maſculine way
of Bowing the Body: and Alarmed with a Rent and Diviſion between the
<hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> who are divided into two Factions,
and Partys; and ſoon meeting with two Pamphlets Puliſhed to acquaint the
World therewith, and that by <hi>G. Keith</hi> who is the Head, and Ringleader,
or Publick Mouth of one Party. And <hi>Thomas Lloyd,</hi> Preſident, and
Deputy Governour, head <hi>of</hi> the other Party; the matter in Difference
was occaſioned by <hi>G. Keith,</hi> his urging them to Publiſh their
Fundamental Truths and Principles, as a Confeſſion of their Faith; and
Unanimouſly agreed upon, which he ſaith has never been yet done; and from
what rent and ſeperation has already ariſen upon the firſt 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:171419:54"/>motion of ſuch a deſign is no difficulty to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
what ſhall Unqueſtionably happen before its accompliſhment; the points
already mentioned where in the Difference Lies; are weighty, Fundamental and
Saving, abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning the only Object of Saving Faith, even Chriſt
Jeſus, God-man, Saviour and Mediator, 2. Concerning the Sufficiency of the
Light in all men to Salvation; which Light they Call Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; and
that I may give a Narrative to the <hi>Word, I</hi> ſhall give a Relation
from their own VVritings, &amp; alſo from their own Teſtimonies, and the
open and publick Diſcourſes of both Parties I Converſt with while at
<hi>Philadelphia.</hi> 1. I ſhall give an Account of what <hi>G. K.</hi> has
Publiſhed in a Book, called, <hi>The Plea of the Innocent,</hi> being a
Vindication of <hi>G. K.</hi> and his Followers, from the falſe Informations,
Judgments and Defamations of <hi>Thomas Lloyd, Samuel Ginnings, John
Simcock</hi> and others, to the number of Twenty Eight. It happened many Months
ago that <hi>Thomas Lloyd</hi> and his Party had ſigned an Epiſtle to the
Monthly and Quarterly Meetings in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> Eaſt and VVeſt
<hi>Jarſey:</hi> Informing them of the tedious Exerciſe and vexatious
Perplexity they met with in their Late Friend <hi>G K</hi> for ſeveral months
paſt, from whence the Reader may warrantably conclude two things: 1 That
there hath been much Diviſion, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, Jangling and Difference among
themſelves, ere it broke forth to publick view; and no private meaſures of
Inſpired Judges could prove effectual for reconciling thoſe divided
Parties, who uſed to take away either juſtly or unjuſtly all thoſe
Differences a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves
about Civil and VVorldly Matters which gives to believe it was a Matter in
Debate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong<pb n="85" facs="tcp:171419:54"/>them of another Nature, <hi>&amp;</hi> of
greater weight, <hi>&amp; of</hi> a conſiderable continuance; ſome ſay
for fifteen Months, e're that Fire of contenton broke forth into a Flame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That theſe Twenty Eight pretended Preachers at this time
look on <hi>George Keith</hi> and conſequently all his Party, none of their
preſent but late Friend, and conſequently now their Enemy; and ſo the
name Friend muſt no longer be a general Epithite or univerſal title
peculiar to that Party, or <hi>George Keith</hi> muſt be only a Late
<hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Occaſion of all this Clamour, <hi>&amp;</hi> Heat, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
by <hi>K.</hi> pag 2. To be an Accuſation of <hi>K</hi> by <hi>W.
Stockdale,</hi> an ancient <hi>Quaker Teacher, For Preaching two
Chriſts;</hi> becauſe he Preached <hi>Faith in Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, &amp;
Faith in Chriſt without;</hi> and if this was a new thing from <hi>K.</hi>
his frequent <hi>Teaching</hi> before, muſt have been void <hi>of</hi>
Chriſt, and ſo Chriſtleſs Sermons; or if he did, it was ſo
obſcurely delivered, that he was never plainly underſtood till now: But
<hi>K</hi> having dealt privately with the ſaid <hi>Stockdale,</hi> but
unſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, laid his complaint before twelve <hi>of</hi> their
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, in a <hi>meeting</hi> at <hi>Rt. Ewers</hi> houſe, who rather
defended and excuſed <hi>Stockdale,</hi> then Condemned him; whereby ten
<hi>of</hi> theſe able <hi>Doctors,</hi> two only diffenting, became as
Guilty <hi>of</hi> Ignorance &amp; Errors as <hi>Stockdale</hi> himſelf. And
next the Yearly Meeting at <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and ſo at length, ſix
ſeveral Meetings had this matter in debate, and under their determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;
who gave ſo ſlender a determination at laſt, that they all appeared
rather at a ſtand and demurr about it; <hi>&amp; K.</hi> Juſtly accuſes
them of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, Ignorance, <hi>&amp;</hi> Unbelief <hi>pag.</hi> 4.
<hi>Reader,</hi> all may eaſily perceive from the unchriſtian Labyrinth, in
which theſe men have involved themſelves about ſo<pb n="86" facs="tcp:171419:55"/>weighty and ſo plain a Fundamental, how great Strangers they are to
the True knowledge of the Goſpel Myſtery <hi>of</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; that
of ſix ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meetings <hi>of</hi> their greateſt Dons, in the three
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Governments, they are in confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Chriſt to be
Believed in, for our Salvation; and underſtand not Chriſt as he is Revealed
in the Scriptures, God Man, Suffering and Dying for us; whence it is evident,
what Chriſt the generality of <hi>Quakers</hi> have been hitherto believing
in; which is clear from the Prayer of <hi>Thomas Fittz-Watter,</hi> at a
Meeting, ſaying, <hi>O God that Dyed in us, and Laid down thy Life in us, and
took it up again. &amp;c.</hi> Which <hi>G. K.</hi> juſtly called
Blaſphemy: if this Spiritual Man, ſuppoſe Chriſt as God Mortal, is
moſt inconſiſtant with Scripture, which affairms; <hi>that to him belongs
Immortatity, and abſolute Eternity;</hi> both <hi>a parte ante &amp;
post:</hi> and by this prayer, directs it to ſomething within himſelf, and
not according to Divine Pattern, to <hi>Our Father in Heaven;</hi> and <hi>Rt.
Young</hi> one of their pretended Teachers ſaid, <hi>that he did not find
Chriſt without in all the Scriptures; and further, that Chriſt, when he
aſcended into the Cloud, was ſeperated from his Body;</hi> and <hi>Arthur
Cook,</hi> accuſed <hi>G. K.</hi> for ſaying, <hi>that Chriſts Body that
was Crucified, and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, is gone into Heaven, and was, and is in heaven;
even the very ſame Body;</hi> which <hi>Cook and</hi> others called a
<hi>Novelty,</hi> impoſed upon his Ancient Brethren. And <hi>John
Simtock</hi> asked <hi>G. K. Did Chriſts Bones, Ariſe;</hi> and <hi>Thomas
Lloyd</hi> did object againſt <hi>G. K.</hi> his impoſing Unſcriptural
Faith on his Bretheren: further, <hi>that Faith in Chriſt without us, as he
Dyed for our ſins and roſe again, was not neceſsary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
and further, <hi>that Christ within did all.</hi> Can any Repeat ſuch
Blaſphemous expreſſions without<pb n="87" facs="tcp:171419:55"/>horrour, when they
conſider the deplorable caſe of ſuch, as are Lead, and Taught by theſe
men; who openly, publickly, and avowedly, profeſs their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<hi>of</hi> the true Chriſt, which is but One, and can be no other; even,
<hi>He that was Born of the Virgin Mary, Suffered in the World, was Crucified
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>was Buried, &amp; Roſe again,
with the ſame Body, having his wounds upon him, as he ſhewed to</hi> Thomas
<hi>the</hi> Apoſtle; <hi>&amp; after ſome time of Converſe in the World,
proving thereby the Reality of his Reſurrection, was received Bodily into a
Cloud, in the open view of his</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>and Aſcended into Heaven,
&amp; now</hi> Sits <hi>at the Right Hand of God the Father, making con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual
interceſſion for ſinners; &amp; the ſame Man-Chriſt, that Liveth for
Ever, &amp; Ever, ſhall come in his Glory, with all his Holy Angels, to Judge
the World in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs at the Laſt Day:</hi> All which is abundantly
teſtified in the Holy Scriptures. And now whoſoever Believes not in
Chriſt, nor receives him as deſcribed in the Word of God; ſeeing he
himſelf ſays, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>They are they that teſtify of
him;</hi> it may warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably be concluded, they believe not in him at all;
&amp; therefore I leave it to others to determine, what ſort of
<hi>Christians Quakers</hi> muſt needs be; and alſo what we muſt judge
<hi>of</hi> their Sufficient, <hi>&amp;</hi> Saving, <hi>&amp;</hi> Divine
Light, of which they have been boaſting univerſally; and magnifying them
ſelves from above all others in the world; and what do they now think of
their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate <hi>Call,</hi> and Apoſtolick <hi>Miſſion,</hi> ſeeing
they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves ſo groſly Ignorant, and ſo much in the dark
about the Foundation of our Salvation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Chriſt Jeſus, who is ſo
fully deſcribed in the very Letter of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And this Breach is Riſen to ſuch a height, that the Railings,
Revilings, bitter &amp; uncharitable Accuſations,<pb n="88" facs="tcp:171419:56"/>they
were wont to vomit maliciouſly, againſt all the Reformed Churches, are now
juſtly turned againſt one another; for <hi>Lloyd</hi> and his Party fly out
againſt <hi>Keith,</hi> calling him a Reviler of the Brethren, Brat of
<hi>Babylon,</hi> Accuſer <hi>of the Brethren;</hi> one that alwayes
endeavoureth to keep down the power of Truth; drawing from the Gift of God;
calling him alſo Pope, Primate of <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> Father
Confeſſor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him of Envy, extream Paſſion, a turbulent &amp;
unſubdued Spirit: Let the Authors of theſe make good their Charge, or let
them take what follows. Shall ever ſuch a man be followed by ſuch as have
given him ſuch a monſtrous Character, as none but the greateſt of
Impoſtors deſerve; and it is obſervable, that in all which <hi>K</hi> has
Publiſhed, for he has carried the day in his Prints; that he has not fairly,
nor fully Explained himſelf, for it wants to be determined, when Chriſt is
ſaid to be in all men, by the name Light; whether he and his Party, who ſay
with all <hi>Quakers,</hi> He is ſubſtantially in them, believe him to be
in them as Mediator and Saviour, as <hi>K.</hi> ſeems to aſſert in his
<hi>Grounds of Separation.</hi> pag. 32 &amp; <hi>William Pen,</hi> in Reaſon
againſt Railing, aſſerts the true Light with which every man is
Enlightned, to be ſufficient for Salvation; and how <hi>Pen, G. K.</hi> and
his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries can jump again into a Knot, after ſo plain and palpable
Difference about their great Fundamental of the Sufficiency of the <hi>Light
within;</hi> I Leave it to other Judges to determine; and it deſerves
obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that in their Epiſtle to their Brethren, and their
Commendation, what high, lofty, and proud Titles <hi>of</hi> Commendation,
ſcarce applicable to men, they gave to <hi>G K.</hi> as, <hi>That he Walked
in the Counſel of God,</hi> was Lovely in that Day, <hi>When the Beauty of
the Lord was upon him, and his Comelineſs covered him;</hi> 
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:171419:56"/>and immediately with the ſame Breath, they throw him
down, and look upon him as <hi>Faſſen from the high Places of</hi>
Iſrael, as a man Slain in his High Places; &amp; as they fix hard names upon
him as formerly; ſo he payes them home again in the ſame Coin; &amp; calls
<hi>Lloyd</hi> and his Party, which are ſome thouſands, <hi>Fools, Ignorant
Heathens, Infidels, Silly Souls, Lyars, Hereticks, Rotten Ranters, Mugg
letonians,</hi> &amp;c So that if we were inclinable to give them Names, we
have no Room, for they have done it to our hands themſelves: And I muſt
confeſs, they are better able than we; for they are better acquainted with
one another, and privy to their Errors, Hereſies, and other <hi>Hidden Works
of Darkneſs,</hi> which they have hitherto been aſhamed to Publiſh to the
World: and yet it is admirable to think, where theſe men find ſuch a
ſtock of Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to wipe their mouths, and ſay they have not Railed
all this while, but all they have ſaid on both ſides, is in the
uprightneſs of their hearts, &amp; all theſe Names given are Truth,
<hi>I</hi> ſhall leave them ſo, diſproving neither; one of
<hi>Lloyds</hi> Party, <hi>William Gabitas</hi> deſired <hi>K</hi> to forbear
Preaching Chriſt without, ſeeing it gave Offeence to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as
<hi>Paul</hi> did concerning Eating of Fleſh: an able Doctor indeed, and very
probable to have Chriſt in him, who valued the Preaching <hi>of</hi> Chriſt
Crucified no more than the Eating of Fleſh; and muſt not ſuch Brethren as
take Offence as ſuch Doctrine be acted by a Diabolical Spirit? <hi>Thomas
Lloyd,</hi> in a Publick Meeting affirmed, no man could differ with <hi>G.
K.</hi> but he was in danger <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> of his Soul by him;
and farther, that he had bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
more vexatious Adverſary to Friends, then <hi>Hicks,</hi> or
<hi>Scanderet,</hi> or the greateſt Enemies; ſure ſuch
Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharitableneſs and Ranchor muſt have great provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, 
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:171419:57"/>&amp; flow from no good Spirit: another proud and ſelf
conceited expreſſion of a plain <hi>Quaker, Muſt, I truckle under
thee;</hi> indeed it was not fit a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhould; and further, <hi>G.
K.</hi> affirmed, That no ſuch Damnable Hereſies, and Doctrines of Devis
were Tolerated in any Proteſtant Society, as among <hi>Quakers,</hi> at
<hi>Philadelphia;</hi> if this Charge is true, I am perſwaded it will extend
to moſt <hi>Quakers</hi> in the World, or they muſt yet be in Confuſion
and Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined about their Principles. Many other moſt dangerous
Poſitions were urged and diſputed among them, ſavouring of nothing but
Blindneſs and Error, as one that owned no man Chriſt Jeſus as Mediator in
Heaven without him, but the Grace of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and alſo that Chriſt was
only a Spirit in Heaven, and had nothing of the Body; and many of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> denying the Day of Judgment, and any
Reſurrection, but what they have already attained; &amp; <hi>John Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſaid, Chriſt was a
Mediator for no Drunkards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
wicked perſons, but for his own Diſciples; many
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them denied Gods Preſence in
all his Creatures, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing moſt ignorantly, and blaſphemouſly: if God be
in Herbs and Graſs, then who tramples on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tramples on God; and this occaſioned a new Diſput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether God be preſent in Lice? Some
denyin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they were any part of the
Creation; another Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that Chriſt Cureth mens Souls perfectly at once
and makes them free of all ſin; and when we
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perfect, we are Kings, and are
not to Beg or Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to God for our
ſelves: another ſays Whether
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Body that was Crucified, be in
Heaven, Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church determine?
one <hi>Samuel Ginnings</hi> declared
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Meeting, <hi>That to do Gods
Buſineſs we needed Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Wiſdom,</hi> but to do our own Buſineſs as men,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> needed it not! another
affirmed, <hi>That a man mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak<pb n="91" facs="tcp:171419:57"/>unſound Words in the
Life;</hi> and at another Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame man bids us wait, <hi>That the
Scepter might depart from</hi> Judah, <hi>that</hi> Shiloh <hi>might come.</hi>
Is it not evident from theſe groſs, impertinent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable
Ignorances, and Blaſphemous Hereſies, <hi>That God has juſtly given them
over to a Spirit of</hi> Deluſion,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o believe the groſſeſt Lyes
that ever was hatcht; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that for
their ambitious and deceiving pretences
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o unwarrantable Inſpirations.
Another Quarrel was, <hi>G. K</hi>'s Objecting againſt their Diſcipline, as
too Looſe; but for my part, I never knew, nor heard
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y they had that was purely
Eccleſiaſtick; &amp; what they pretended to was moſt abſolute and
arbitrary: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho' I underſtand of
late <hi>G. K.</hi> had Compoſed a new Draught in many particulars, which
tho' not allowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Reading at
their Yearly Meeting, yet was ſent to the Yearly Meeting at <hi>London,</hi>
for their Approbation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
Sanction: of which I ſhall give my Reader a ſmall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt in theſe following
particulars: 1. That all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l
Friends ſhall give in a few words leſs or more a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure Confeſſion unto the Truth
generally Received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Friends. 2.
If Friends be ſatisfied with this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, they are to expreſs their Chriſtian Love, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnifie their owning them, by
taking them by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, or giving
the hand unto them. 3 That all friends who have Children come to years of
Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, whom they have
Inſtructed in the Principles <hi>of</hi> Truth, that they further Labour with
their Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be willing to
be Received into the Number of friends, in the manner above mentioned. 4.
Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er there ſhould not be
Elders and Deacons Choſen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d
Appointed, and Named by the Conſent of the hole Church, for the Help and
Aſſiſtance of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iends of
the Miniſtry. 5. That no raw and unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed perſons do preſume to ſpeak or pray in the 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:171419:58"/>Meetings, until they give proof of their ſound
Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Experience, and Spiritual Abilities to their Elder Brethren, the
Elders and the Church. 6. That no Friends joyn in Marriage with any, but ſuch
as are Received into the Society of Fiends, by a ſolemn Confeſſion of
their Faith, and Profeſſion of Truth in the manner aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Theſe are but a few of many Articles of the like nature, which
had a very cold Reception, that tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they did not allow it a publick Reading, yet cry'd it down as
downright Popery; but ſure if this take place, <hi>Quakers</hi> will look
with another Face then ever they have yet done; and many of their ſilly,
igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and impertinent, and blaſpemous Teachers, ſhall be laid aſide
as uſeleſs. And the Breach was ſo great, that the two Emiſſaryes from
<hi>London, T. W.</hi> and <hi>J. D.</hi> was ſo far from accompliſhing a
Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leation, that they Condemned him for the Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pronounced
Woes againſt him; and <hi>J. D.</hi> compared the Difference there, to
Childrens falling out about trifles; ſure theſe men ſo much admired at
<hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and elſewhere, diſcover both their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and
weakneſs in joyning with the ſtrongeſt Party, the Magiſtrates; and
looking upon the <hi>Doctrine of Christ Crucifyed,</hi> and the <hi>Sufficiency
of the Light within</hi> to be but Trifles.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>G. K.</hi> is blamed for calling <hi>W.
Stockdal,</hi> and a whole Meeting, ignorant Heathens; but ſays
<hi>Keith,</hi> it there is Light ſufficient to Salvation in all men without
the man Chriſt, then an honeſt Heathen is a true Chriſtian; hence every
man may Learn, That honeſt Heathens are good <hi>Quakers,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quakers</hi> are good
Heathens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Keith</hi> having his Sentence, Lay under Charges and
no poſſibility of obtaining (as he ſays
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:171419:58"/>any
redreſs or Goſpel Order; but it is ſtrange that any man of Senſe,
ſhould expect order from I gnorance; Diſtraction, and Confuſion, as the
whole Scheme of this Controverſy appears to be to every Rational and
conſidering Man; he at Length breaks off, &amp; ſeparates from their
Society, and ſets up for himſelf. Firſt at his own Houſe, and generally
ſince, at the <hi>Barbado</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Philade phia;</hi> and as he
endeavours to Juſtify himſelf from all former Imputations, ſo he
eſſays a Vindication of the Late Separation which he does by a
<hi>Pamphlet,</hi> called the, <hi>Reaſons and Cauſes thereof;</hi> which I
ſhall give my Reader as Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>Thomas Lloyd,</hi> ſo far failed in
Proving his Charge againſt <hi>G. K. For denying the ſufficiency of the
Light within;</hi> and after Judgment was paſſed, by a Monthly Meeting at
<hi>Philadelphia,</hi> the 22<hi>d</hi> of the 12th Month 1691. Would not give
forth a Paper <hi>of</hi> Condemnation <hi>of</hi> his Falſe Charge: but any
may perceive <hi>K</hi>'s cunning, who not only eſcaped the Juſt Judgment
of this Meeting, according to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uakers</hi> Principles, but by denying the charge with a
Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, made his accuſer guilty; for as he declared before, and
ſince ſaying, <hi>the Light within is not ſuf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ficient without the Man Chriſt
Without us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Reaſon for his Seperation, becauſe <hi>K</hi>'s
Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts kept a Publick Meeting, in the Afternoon at the Bank, without
the conſent of the whole Body <hi>of</hi> Friends there; which <hi>K</hi>
ſays ſhould be univerſal, &amp; Unanimous, and not by any Plurality of
Votes: and ſo <hi>G. K.</hi> and his party kept a Meeting for that Day in the
Afternoon at his own Houſe, which he called Private, and finding as they
ſay, they reſolved to continue the Seperation, which is ſtill done. I
would Amimadvert the Reader, that the Second Reaſon is<pb n="94" facs="tcp:171419:59"/>Frivolous, ariſing from a Nicety and circumſtance of Place, which
as carryed by a Plurality of Votes, tho' <hi>K</hi> would not ſubmit to it,
without the Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Conſent of all; which he ſays is the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed method
of Friends; but it is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if the Plurality had determined for
him, he would never have gone about to invalidate the determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if
the Unanimous conſent of all be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in ſuch triflles, we expect
<hi>K</hi> will do nothing in greater Matters without it. 3. <hi>Reaſon:</hi>
becauſe moſt Groſs, and Uuchriſtian Errors, againſt the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental
Doctrines of the Chriſtian Faith, are held by divers of them that are Publick
Teachers, &amp; many are Unqualified for the Miniſtry; this is a weighty
Ground indeed, and a juſt Cauſe; and it is not to be doubted, but
applicable to both Partys; ſo that a ſeperation from them both is
Warrantable, which all good Chriſtians are to pray that God may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh
to the Glory of his own Name, and the Honour of Truth as the Iſſue of the
begun Controverſy and Confuſions; and alaſs! it muſt be ſtrange, that
all theſe things have been concealed ſo long ſince the Riſe of
<hi>Quakers in Europe,</hi> and none found Faithful or Zealou s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or Truth among them, to bring them to
Light until this very Prejudice, Paſſion, and Malice, or envy among them;
for it is not to be doubted, but <hi>K</hi> in his Travels over the World,
could not meet with as many Inſufficient Teachers as are now among them, in
the Government of <hi>Penſilvania, Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Jerſys;</hi>
and alſo Innumerable impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cys, Inconſiſtencys, Errors, and
Falſhoods, as he has been ſenſible of, of late, abounds among them; ſo
that it is to be feared, he has been moved from Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, Paſſion, and
other Quarrels, whereby he has taken this time and place, for aſſuming the
Honour <hi>of</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:171419:59"/>New Reformer; for what he charges them
with, is no New thing, but known by all who have converſt with that Party, to
have been their Conſtant Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as much known to <hi>K,</hi> as any now
in being, for the Time he has followed that Novelty. And according to the
Preſent State of Affairs, and Notable Alterations in a Place, ſo the
Diſcourſes of all Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and Directed, for moſt places of this
Province; this Diviſion has given all Partys a Theme of Diſcourſe, and
Subject <hi>of</hi> Debate, and <hi>K</hi> in his Poſtſcript to his
<hi>Reaſons,</hi> gives a Brief account of the matters Contro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſed, both
at Meeting and other Places, we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for the Information <hi>of</hi>
Inſpired Men. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Whether we are only to believe in Chriſt Within or in
him without alſo, and in Heaven Our <hi>Advocate with the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether to Preach Faith in Chriſt within, and Faith in
Chriſt without, be to Preach two Chriſts? 3. Whether it be a Doctrine
neceſſary to be Preacht, to Believe in Chriſt without? 4 Whether
Chriſt's Body that was Nailed to the Croſs, and was Buried, and Aroſe
again, be with him in Heaven? Some of them ſaying, as <hi>Keith</hi> told me
at his Houſe, it never Roſe, but Evaniſhed, or Remained in the Grave:
others ſaying, it aroſe, but after it Aſcended in the Cloud, was
ſeparated from it: others ſay, it is a Nicety, and to be ignorant of it,
does not hinder a man from being a true Chriſtian, and a Miniſter of
Chriſt: Others ſaying, it is a dividing of Chriſt. O<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers accuſing of
ſome, for Denying the <hi>Sufficiency of the Light within;</hi> from all
which it is evident, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of all their high pretences to
Immediate inſpirations, and Extraordinary Illuminations from he Spirit of
God, what great Error, Ignorance, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lindneſs, they diſcover to the
World. 1. Their<pb n="96" facs="tcp:171419:60"/>Ignorance of Chriſt Jeſus our Saviour,
<hi>whom to Know is Eternal Life;</hi> and whom <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay, is,
&amp; dwells ſubſtantially in all of them; and if ſo, could it be
poſſible to Remain ſo I gnorant of him, as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim themſelves to
be; and who in their right wits, but muſt look upon them as deluded Souls,
rather than Inſpired from Heaven. 2. They know not how neceſſary the
Faith and Knowledge of the true Chriſt as Mediator, is, to make a true
Chriſtian, &amp; real Miniſter; hence they plainly tell us, what
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Miniſters will paſs among <hi>Quakers,</hi> even ſuch
as neither know Chriſt aright, nor believe the true Knowledge of him
neceſſary; ſeeing they call Chriſt-man, Aſcended and Glorified in
Heaven, a Nicety; conclude all ſuch, Chriſtleſs Chriſtians, and
Chriſtleſs Miniſters.</p>
            <p>As an Appendix to the reaſons, we have an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Faith
<hi>of Quakers,</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Keith,</hi> and called in its
Frontiſpiece, the Faith of ſome <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in
<hi>Penſilvania,</hi> which is an Argument of their difference in Principles,
and Fundamentals; but this will not do, being ſo far from being
<hi>Quakers</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples every where, that they are not even the
Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and for any thing I know, but of
a very few; <hi>for</hi> tho' itis the Ambition <hi>of</hi> both Parties, to
Increaſe their Numbers, &amp; Engroſs Followers, yet to this Account of
Faith, he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured but five Subſcribers, beſide himſelf; and as I am
Informed, men of mean Parts, and Account; but that I may briefly animadvert all
Lovers of Truth, concerning this Account of Faith, which ſhould be
Fundamentals chiefly; I ſhall deliver ſomething in general, and ſomething
particularly: And in general 1. It is more guilty of Deficiency and
Omiſſion, then a Catechiſm lately Cenſured by him, to which he has 
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:171419:60"/>an Anſwer; for there are none acquainted with
<hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Principles, can conclude this Account to be <hi>Faithfu</hi>
or <hi>Full</hi> 2 Their Faith is here ſo obſcurely delivered in Scripture
Language in controverſy, as to the Expoſition of them, between them and the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, that, except in ſome few things, that are not
Fundamentals, they are the Faith <hi>of</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as of
<hi>Quakers;</hi> and ſo not fairly done. But particularly; 1 In page 29.
<hi>He owns a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Election of all that ſhall be Saved, before the
Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the World:</hi> which he muſt never recede <hi>from.</hi> 2
Page 30. He is lame in deſcribing the Corruption <hi>conveyed from Adam to
his Poſterity;</hi> and ſays, <hi>It is not Imputed to Damnation;</hi> but
if there be any Sin not Damnable with <hi>Quakers,</hi> Death muſt not be the
<hi>Wages of Sin</hi> with them; neither muſt the <hi>Loſs of our Original
Righteouſneſs, or the Image of God be Damnable:</hi> Strange flattering
Doctrine to Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sinners 3. He ſays, Page 31. <hi>That the common
Miniſtration, which they ſay is in all, even in their meer Gentile State,
is of a Saving Nature, &amp; tendency<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>in a general way;</hi> ſo that any may ſee what a Change is in
this mans mind, from all <hi>Quakers,</hi> who ſtill have aſſerted the
Sufficiency of this Univerſal Grace, for Salvation; for here he neither calls
it Sufficient, nor Saving; but only it is of a Saving Nature and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; and
yet Page 32. He contradicted by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is ſufficient to Save every
man. 4 He omits wholly any thing concerning the <hi>Covenants of Works, and
Grace,</hi> which are undoubtedly main points of Faith; ſeeing it is
according to the Tenour of the Covenant of Grace, every Sinner muſt be Saved,
and Chriſt is Mediator <hi>of the New Covenant.</hi> 5. He tells us nothing
of Women Teachers at all in his Section concerning, but perhaps he dare not
tell his<pb n="98" facs="tcp:171419:61"/>mind yet in that point, as he ſays of other
things. 6. He Tranſiently runs over the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 7. He continues to
cry down Swearing, in Witneſſing to Truth; while they decry the name, they
really maintain and practice the thing in all Courts in <hi>Penſilvania.</hi>
8. He fills up a whole Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Faith, with Baptiſm, and the Lords
Supper; but ſeeing it is known to all, they deny the uſe of both, they
ſhould be aſhamed ever to Treat of them at all; eſpecially among their
Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals; for he might as well have filled up a Section with
<hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſsover:</hi> if it be only to deceive,
this is no ingenuous dealing. 9. If plain Language and plain Habits be
Fundamentals with <hi>Quakers,</hi> what need is there of any other mark to
know a <hi>Quaker</hi> by: and why the Language of others, are not as plain as
<hi>Quakers,</hi> I know not; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, as <hi>Jacob Tilman,</hi> when
Preaching &amp; Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Dutch,</hi> to an <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Congregation. Laſtly, I fear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ording to his Deſcription of the Church of Chriſty who ought,
as he ſayes, to manifeſt their Faith, to one another, by the Confeſſion
of the mouth; there will no ſuch be found among Quakers, who never had any
publick, and unanimous Confeſſion of their Faith, yet extant; otherwiſe
there would be no room for the preſent Diviſion, about the greateſt of
Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals. In the next place, I proceed to take notice of <hi>G.K</hi>'s
Appeal from the twenty eight Judges, and it has a cunning and ambiguous Title,
<hi>viz. To the Spirit of Truth &amp; true Judgment, in all Faithful Friends
called</hi> Quakers; <hi>that meet at the Yearly Meeting at</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lington;
whereby any man may perceive, if they judge and determine againſt him, he has
a back Door to fly out at, and will not ſtand to their judgment; therefore
his Appeal is moſt idle, and<pb n="99" facs="tcp:171419:61"/>an empty Bravado; for either
he looks on them, as Competent Judges, or not; if competent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, why does
he not ſubmit himſelf to their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, without ſuch a Reſervation; or
thus, if he believes them to have the Spirit of Truth, why does he ſcruple a
ſubmiſſion to the judgment of Friends, as <hi>Quakers</hi> are commonly
called, if they have not the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> whether it were not
ſafer to wave the Appeal which has the ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a dubious Oracle, for
ſtill it muſt terminate here; if the whole Meeting ſhould not be of
<hi>K</hi>'s Judgment, he ſhall declare them deſtitute of the Spirit <hi>of
Truth, and void of true judgment;</hi> for he has diſapproved the plurality
<hi>of</hi> Votes in another caſe. And in the Appeal, there is firſt by way
of Preamble, the Grounds thereof laid down; and next, twelve particulars by way
of Query propoſed, to be Debated at the ſaid Yearly Meeting, which highly
offended the Governour, with the reſt of the Magiſtracy that were
<hi>Quakers;</hi> and particularly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them, tho' it is all along by way
of Queſtion, with giving a Commiſſion to, and hiring me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, by recovering a Sloop from
Privateers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Principles of <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are againſt
<hi>be uſe of the Carnal Weapon, which they tranſgreſs alſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y providing the Indians with
Powder, and Lead, to fight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt other Indians; and alſo that one of thoſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Ministers Taught, not to take an Eye
for an Eye; &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſhort
time, by paſſing Sentence on Malefactors, takes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife for Life; and finally
enquires, whether there is any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xample for it in Scripture, or in all</hi> Chriſtendom, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Miniſters ſhould Ingroſs the
Worldly Government, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they do
in</hi> Philadelphia, <hi>which hath proved of very
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il tendency.</hi> Now the laſt
particular proves ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſive,
Governour <hi>Lloyd</hi> after ſome Conſultation,<pb n="100" facs="tcp:171419:62"/>ſends <hi>for</hi> a Taylor, who had Nail'd up the Appeal on a Board
at his Shop Window, to publick view; and after ſome Examination, he told
them, he was not a ſhamed, to look Perſecutors in the Face, but being
Required to give Securities, to anſwer the Quarter Seſſions; they gave
him till to morrow morning, to provide them; but from what ſharp Retorting
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, he gave them, he was diſmiſſed without any further noiſe:
but immediately ſent for the Printer, and Requiring Securities of him, which
he denied; his <hi>Shop</hi> was Searched, and all the ſaid Papers, and his
Printing Letters, to the value of Ten Pounds <hi>Sterling,</hi> as <hi>K.</hi>
ſays, were taken away; and the ſaid Printer, <hi>William Bradford</hi> was
Committed to the Sheriffs Houſe as a Priſon. And another <hi>John
Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>komb,</hi> ſent for, and Committed, for Selling ſome of the ſaid
Papers at his Houſe, all which was done in a Legal Mittimus, charging the
Printer, and Seller as Publiſhers; which was a miſtake, for properly the
Author is the Publiſher; &amp; this makes a great noiſe, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in City and Countrey, that
<hi>Quakers</hi> begin to Impriſon and Perſecute one another, proving what
they would do to others if they had power, opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and provocation; but
to wipe off all ſuſpicio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of
Perſecution, they make uſe of the ſame plea as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Perſecutors do, even the Diſturbance of the
Peace, and Subverſion of the Government: but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Salve will not Cure the Sore: The next meaſure
taken, is, to Conſult how to puniſh <hi>G. K.</hi> the known Author; and as
many of the Subſcribers as were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Goverment: and next day being
the 26<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Auguſt</hi> a
Conclave was appointed; but two o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the Commiſſioners being no <hi>Quakers,</hi> Diſſenting, they could not
bring it to bear, to Sign a Mittimus, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Committing <hi>K;</hi> therefore next day, reſolves to
publiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:171419:62"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, or his Abetters from
publiſhing any ſuch Seditious Papers for the future; but it is
Obſervable, that in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation there is not any mention made of Their
Majeſties Names; which every Loyal Subject muſt Reſent; but of the Late
K. twice, notwithſtanding they had Caution given, to mention what King they
meant, <hi>Verbum ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Sapienti</hi> But the former Priſoners continue ſtill in Confinement; which
is palpable and moſt evident Partiality, to puniſh the Printer &amp;
Seller, and ſuffer the known Author, and Subſcribers to eſcape. But on
the <hi>Monday</hi> following, the Appeal, with the Mittimus, and a
Poſtſcript is Reprinted; and in the Poſtſcript, as is very Remarkable,
that it is Aſſerted by <hi>K</hi> that it is contrary to <hi>Quakers</hi>
princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to make uſe of the <hi>Carnal Weapon;</hi> but they found in
their Experience, it was impoſſible to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Magiſtracy without it,
that is, the <hi>Carnal Sword;</hi> who can but ſmile to ſee theſe men
overthrowing their own Principles, by aſſerting the Inconſiſtency of
them with Magiſtracy, which is an Ordinance of God; and conſequently no
Government ſhould be put into <hi>Quakers</hi> Hands: But great things were
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Yearly Meeting at <hi>Burlington,</hi> which was to begin
within few days; tho' little expectation of a Friendly Accommodation; for
<hi>G. K.</hi> kept out of Town, leſt he ſhould by a Priſon, be prevented
to attend that Meeting; but <hi>K</hi> came off there with Flying Colours; for
the other Party being Summo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned again and again to Appear, but declined it:
Whether they diſowned the Authority of that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſuſpected the
badneſs of their Cauſe, which they had reaſon to do, or feared <hi>G.
K.</hi> his Party to be too ſtrong, they can beſt anſwer for themſelves
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t that Meeting juſtify<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>G. K.</hi> and condemned <hi>Lloyd</hi> 
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:171419:63"/>and his Party, diſcharging them to Teach or Pray in publick
Meetings, till they had condemned their former Judgment, by a publick Writing;
and how this Order was ſlighted, is too palpable to be denied; both Parties
are diſcharged from Railing, which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes both were guilty; but while
the Meeting at <hi>Burlington</hi> clears <hi>K.</hi> the Yearly Meeting at
<hi>Maryland,</hi> condemns him, and juſtifies the other Party, whereby that
Infallible Diſcerning Spirit <hi>Quakers</hi> boaſt of, &amp; lay is in
every true <hi>Quaker,</hi> is overthrown; for great Meetings of their
greateſt Dons, can be miſtaken, &amp; make contrary and contradictory
Orders. I am In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the Diviſion has Reached <hi>England;</hi> for in
<hi>London,</hi> one Party who were againſt <hi>Keith,</hi> bought up all his
Pamphlets, to prevent the Spreading of the Difference: Another Party Orders a
new Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of all his Books, relating to that Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy; this I
had lately of one of themſelves. I ſhall conclude with ſome paſſages
from undoubted Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
One affirmed the Difference at preſent concerning Chriſt, was an empty
Barrel; from whence it is evident, what mean thoughts this Zealote had of
Chriſt, as Man 2. Another ſaid, he did not believe to be Saved by that
which Dyed at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> What a poor caſe muſt ſuch a Soul be
in? 3. <hi>John Delaval</hi> hath expreſt his fear that <hi>Cotton
Mather</hi>'s Propheſie of <hi>G.K</hi> is now accompliſhing. Laſtly,
there is among <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> one <hi>Jacob,</hi>
a <hi>Dutchman,</hi> who takes upon him to Preach and Pray in the
<hi>Dutch</hi> Language, to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, pretending an
Immediate Call thereunto, which <hi>John Delaval,</hi> and the Teachers Son in
law, uſed to Interpret, for the underſtanding of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ſome
time after, the Hearers deſired the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eters to
forbear, for they were more Edified<pb facs="tcp:171419:63"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithout Interpretation, then with it; though they
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderſtood not a word he ſaid;
would any have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppoſed there was
ſuch blind implicite Faith out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that theſe Spiritual
Profeſſors ſhould lay open their Deluſions to the VVorld, at ſo plain
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate.</p>
            <p>But what impreſſion the Loſs of their Governmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay have, and what Alterations
<hi>it</hi> may make amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, I leave to Further
Information. And whoev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> would have
more of this Nature, <hi>even the Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> War among</hi> Quakers, <hi>chiefly promoted by the Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Weapon of the Tongue;</hi> I
recommend them to <hi>Phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elphia,</hi> for an enlargement of this
Narrative Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s all their own, excepting ſome
Obſervations, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
Animadverſions on both Sides.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere is now in the Preſs, &amp; will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be Publiſhed: A
new book, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Preſent to be given to Teeming Women,</hi> by
their Husbands or Friends. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Directions for <hi>Women</hi> with
<hi>Child.</hi> How to Prepare for the Hour of TRAVAIL. Written firſt for the
Private Uſe of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of <hi>Quality:</hi> and now Publiſhed for
the common good. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>John
Oliver.</hi> Firſt Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and Received with great
<hi>Commendation,</hi> and general <hi>Acceptation:</hi> And
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>printed and Sold at <hi>Boston</hi> in
<hi>New-England,</hi> by <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi> at the Sign of the BIBLE,
over-againſt the <hi>Blew-Anchor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171419:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
